<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The life and light of a man in Christ</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 150KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 83 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88134</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99869041</idno>
  <idno type="VID">170691</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240938545</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2020</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1206_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R210223</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99869041</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99869041e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88134)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170691)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 256:E1206[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The life and light of a man in Christ</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 165, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Pain,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDC.X.L.V.I.I. [1647]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With two final errata leaves.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Jesus Christ --  Knowableness --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170691:1"/>
            <p>THE LIFE and LIGHT of a man IN CHRIST.</p>
            <q>
               <p>But covet earnestly the best gifts, and yet shew I unto you a more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent way. <bibl>
                     <hi>1. Cor. 12.13.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>Prove all things, hold fast that which is good. <bibl>
                     <hi>1. Thes. 5.21.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1. Cor. 2.1, 2. ver.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>And I bretheren, when I came to you, came not with excellency of speech, or of wisdome, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring unto you the testimony of God.</p>
               <p>For I determined not to know any thing among you, save <hi>Iesus Christ,</hi> and him crucified.</p>
            </q>
            <q>Who shall not feare the O Lord, and glorify thy name? For thou onely art holy. <bibl>
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 15.4.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>Thomas. Pain,</hi> MD.C.X.L.V.I.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:170691:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170691:2"/>
            <head>The Preface.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Eare child of God, whose soul &amp; body is consecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted &amp; united, unto the true light &amp; love of Christ thy eternall <hi>wel-being,</hi> who saves the from thy sins. Having had some sad &amp; serious thoughts of the present condition of all sorts of People, but especially of those of the three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, concerning true Religion, which should be built upon truth. And find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to the sorrow of my soul (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing my most charitable thoughts) the dolefull discent of the Religion now professed, from truth, I was like unto a troubled and astonished man, who seeth his dearely beloved friend lying upon the deep water, in great danger to be drowned, and can make him no reliefe,
<pb facs="tcp:170691:3"/> otherwise, then by abrupt thoughts and wishings. <hi>Charity</hi> did bid me looke up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the divided <hi>Churches</hi> of Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as people following their light; <hi>truth</hi> did bid me looke upon the most part of them; as <hi>buyers</hi> and <hi>sellers</hi> in their <hi>Temple Religions.</hi> Thus was me Soul conflicted, betwixt <hi>charity</hi> in it's largest extent, and <hi>divine truth</hi> in it's pure simplicity: But <hi>Truth</hi> at last o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercame my unsoundly grounded <hi>cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> as the <hi>Sun</hi> doth the <hi>darke</hi> Myst, and b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>came an Ambassadour, sent un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me by the King of <hi>Love,</hi> that I shoul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as a faithfull Servant, and lover of <hi>truth,</hi> not mind my own things, but the things that might do good to my dearly beloved indangered friends, <hi>the Lords People,</hi> preferring the good of my br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther, before mine own. Whereupon di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine communicative love, <hi>like unto new Wine,</hi> began to seek a vent in my spirit, and commanded me to write this little <hi>Treatise,</hi> for thy sake, and f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:170691:3"/> thy good, as also for the good of any of Gods creatures in these times of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention amongst people, concerning the way of <hi>Truth.</hi> And here again I had a great conflict, for there did arise a three-fold opposition to diswade me. The first, was a conscientiou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nesse of my in-abillity, which <hi>Moses-like</hi> did plead <hi>Stammering lips.</hi> The second was l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>st any one of the divided <hi>Congregations</hi> should conceive me to be a rayler again them. The third was, that this little treatise, should either not be understood or else be branded with the aspersion of error, in regard, that the most part of men, and Proffessors in these times, &amp; especially the persons who out-strip the rest in knowledge, (as they call it) are so in naturalized, and baptized, in the principles of their own understandings, that the <hi>true light</hi> is little otherwise e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steemed of by them, then <hi>false light is</hi> esteemed of by a <hi>Child</hi> of <hi>true light;</hi> which three difficulties, although they
<pb facs="tcp:170691:4"/> did strive each one more then another to disswade the casting in of this <hi>widows mite,</hi> into the treasury of this <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration:</hi> Yet divine authority did silence their pleading, and convinced their rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, saying to the first, <hi>It is not yee that speake, but the Spirit of your heavenly father speaketh in you, Math. 10.20.</hi> To the second, <hi>But with me it is a very smal thing, that J should be judged of mans judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, 1. Cor. 4.3.</hi> To the third, <hi>my sheep heare my voice Ioh. 10.27.</hi> Thus (deare Reader) am I encouraged and set on worke, to present unto thy view, this little treatise, intituled <hi>the Life and Light of a man in Christ;</hi> Jf thou be one of those who affect curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>osity of speech, rather then the <hi>truths of Jesus,</hi> it may be, that in stead of being bettered by it, thou mayest be the worse by mocking it, and so it will become a stumbling blocke to the, for it commeth to the, not with excellency of speech, or
<pb facs="tcp:170691:4"/> intising words of mans wisdome, &amp;c, <hi>1. Cor. 2.1, 4.</hi> If thou be one of those who without just ground, doest brand truth with error, and so exclaim and chaffe against it, take heed that thy ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claiming and chaffing, be not against it, but against the Lord, as <hi>Moses said</hi> to the People, If thou be one of those, who art sensibly sitting in the region and shadow of death &amp; dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and panting after the light, make use of this little Treatise, as a love to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken sent unto the, <hi>from the Father of Lights,</hi> who himselfe will lead the out of the darke pits of the worlds darknes, in due time. But if thou be one of those who through Christ art one with God, this litle <hi>Treatise</hi> can adde nothing to thy good, <hi>[supream good I mean]</hi> for thou hast that supream good, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that supream Good hath the, which this little <hi>Treatise</hi> testifyeth of.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in the obedience of truth and love.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:170691:5"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> That a man in Christ, doth not adde unto, nor diminish from, the pure word of God.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is true, and cannot be denyed, but that those who by all meanes do labour, to have &amp; keep the divine Scriptures, pure and simple, from humane ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, or detraction, are in that particular nearer the truth, then those who do adde unto, and dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish from the same: But it is no lesse true, and no lesse to be denyed, that many who do earnestly vindicate the written word of God, from ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, or detraction, of the meer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions
<pb n="1" facs="tcp:170691:5"/> of men, do grievously, and grosly, both adde unto, and detract from <hi>the All-truth working Will and Spirit of the God of Scripture,</hi> and of all things else; the which thing, that it may evidently appeare, and be made good upon abso<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ute g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ounds of truth, and not out of a bitter and rayling humour [which in the sight and judgement of the God of mercy, meeknes and Love, is no lesse evill in the <hi>Rayler,</hi> then in the deservedly <hi>rayled upon</hi>] I shall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat in the Bowels of <hi>Love,</hi> all you whosoever that read this <hi>Treatise,</hi> that you would as the Disciples of Christ, <hi>without disparagement of you Reformation, personall righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and knowledge</hi> as you call it, looke upon, and learn at a man in Christ, how he doth not adde un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, nor diminish from the pure word of the Lord, comparatively with your not adding unto, nor di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minishing
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:170691:6"/> from the same, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the truth of Christ, beareth an absolute authority, and invinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble proofe to &amp; in it selfe, although it be barely spoken; yet seing your manner is to affect prooffs of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, for what some men speak, and write, [and it were very well done, if yee could rellish nothing but ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved truth] I shall endeavour in the vertue of <hi>Christ,</hi> to build upon no other foundation, except these two, namely, <hi>the divine life of Christ in the holy Scriptures,</hi> and <hi>the divine word of Christ in the same,</hi> in holding out the <hi>life of a man in Christ,</hi> in this point: As also <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>is life</hi> in the points following.</p>
               <p>A man in Christ, is no further a man in Christ, <hi>then Christ is, and lives in him,</hi> as Christ is, and lives in him, he is and lives in Christ. Even so the body is no further a living body, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the living soul is and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170691:6"/> in the body; as the living soul is, and liveth in the body, the body is active and liveth in the soul; this divine truth, did the truth it selfe, the Lord Christ teach his Disciples, when he said, <hi>Abide in me, and I in you; as the branch cannot beare fruit of it selfe except it abide in the Vine, no more can yee, except ye abide in me. Ioh.</hi> 15.4. So that a man in Christ, is no other thing, but a mysticall subject or body passive, in which the holy Spirit of God and Christ, in an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perative manifestation, fulfilleth all righteousnes, leadeth into all truth, subjecteth the subject in which it acteth to it selfe, whose fruits and effects is most sweetly set forth in the 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. now this, almighty and divine spirit living in a man in Christ, is no way contradictory to it selfe, in adding to, or detracting from, its own pure word; either ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall or internall, the externall is
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170691:7"/> the written word, which the holy men of God spake as they were moved by the holy Ghost, 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.21. the internall, is the spirit &amp; life of the externall, &amp; of all things else which have spirit and life; accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the divine truth of that Scripture, <hi>For of him, and to him, and through him are all things, to whom be glory forever, Amen.</hi> Rom. 11.5. the end of the externall word, is the operative will of the internall word manifesting it self into action, unto which the externall word, is a testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, according to the divine truth of that Scripture, <hi>Search the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures for in them ye think ye have eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life, and they are they that t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>stfy o me.</hi> Ioh 5, 39. The will, mind, and end of the internall operative spirit, and life, is to be a living active Lord God, in a dead passive creatu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the divine truth of these Scriptures, <hi>I live, yet not I, but Christ
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:170691:7"/> liveth in me; and the life which</hi> I <hi>now live in the flesh, I live by the faith of the son of God.</hi> Gal. 2.20. And again, <hi>For you are dead, and your life is hid with Christ in God. Col.</hi> 3.3. This now [the Lord to be a living active God, in a dead passive creature] is the very substance of <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell;</hi> according to the divine truth of that Scripture, <hi>For what the Law could not do, in that it was weake through the fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>sh, God sending his own son, in the likenesse of sinfull flesh, and for sin condemned sin in the flesh, that the righteousnes of the law might be fulfilled in us; who walk not after the flesh, but after the spirit.</hi> Rom. 8.3, 4. This as <hi>Solomon</hi> saith, is, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusion of the whole matter? <hi>Feare God and keep his commandements: for this is the whole duty of man.</hi> Ecles. 12.13. which place is expounded according to God and truth in <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.13. thus, <hi>worke out your own salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:170691:8"/> with feare and trembling; for it is God which worketh in you both to will, and to doe, of his good pleasure,</hi> this as Christ the truth it selfe saith, is eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life; because it is the only true knowledge of the onely true God, &amp; Iesus Christ whom he hath sent, and this is that pure word of God, unto which, and from which a man in Christ, as he is in Christ, doth neither adde unto, nor diminish from; therefore in so far as <hi>creature man</hi> will be more then a dead pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sive creature, in so far he addeth to the pure word of God: and in so far as by evill and sin, he b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing but a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite creature, liveth, and acteth in himselfe, himselfe not being his own creature, but Gods creature, in so farre he diminisheth from the pure word of God. Let every one that readeth this little Book, bring them selves to a true impartial triall here, and if they do, they will find them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:170691:8"/> at a farther distance, from the true life of a man in Christ, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this point, then they were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of, yea they will heare the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly spirit of God, and their own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences uttering such speeches with in themselves, against themselves, as they would tearme madnes, bitternes and error, being uttered by the mouth of man unto them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> That a man in Christ doth not approve of sinne.</head>
               <p>AS the Sun cannot send forth darknes, but light, so the Sun of righteousnes and purity in a man in Christ cannot send forth, or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of sin, but purity and holines; for sin is both contrary to purity &amp; holines, and is the want of purity &amp; holines. Notwithstanding, as it is possible, that sometimes clouds may inte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n betwixt a man who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteth
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170691:9"/> to be in the Sun-shine, and the Sun: so it is possible, that some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time, yea frequently, yea ordinari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the Serpent, and will of man, may insinuate it selfe, betwixt the soul of a man in Christ, and Christ, and say, yea, hath God said thou shalt be a dead passive creature and he a living acting God? Doe thou the contrary, be thou a living active creature, for in so doing thou shalt be as God; here now is a battle betwixt <hi>Michael</hi> and the <hi>Dragon,</hi> betwixt <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Goliah,</hi> betwixt the <hi>seed of the Woman</hi> and the <hi>seed of the</hi> SERPENT, betwixt the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Christ and the Devill.</p>
               <p>And this is that onely sin, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing else, which is sin in the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a man in Christ.</p>
               <p>And in this point, a man in Christ doth much differ from many who do confesse sin, and who professe hatred against it: for he is like unto
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:170691:9"/> a chast wife, who for the true love she beares unto her own true hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, would tremble at the very thoughts of lying with a Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aster; which act her soul abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eth: But those that are not men in Christ, are like unto a lustfull de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded woman, who runneth away with another womans Husband, and entereth into a false matrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny with him; and notwithstanding that God and her own conscience doth tell her she liveth in sin; yet through the lust of the flesh, and conceit of mariage, she prostituteth her body to the man, and liveth in whoredome; but if it shall come to passe, that shee fall into whoredome with another man, besides this her falsly conceived husband: then she takes on heavily, and is much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced; but she liveth in whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, although she should not play he whore with others besides this
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170691:10"/> man; because he is not her true but the false husband. and although she conceive a greater evill, in her play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the whore with another then with this man, yet the evill is no lesse, in playing the whore with this man, then with another.</p>
               <p>Even so, those that are not with a man in <hi>Christ,</hi> baptized into a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving active God, and a dead passive creatures, but will live and act in, and think that they have warrant and liberty so to do; they are like unto this adulterous woman, often times convinced about this, &amp; that predominant sin (as they call it) when as this predominant sinne of theirs, is nothing so grievous unto them, and in their eyes, as their not being baptized into a living active God, and a dead passive creature, is grievous unto, and in the eyes of God and truth; For it is the very fountain and spring, of all their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dominants:
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170691:10"/> according to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine truth of that Scripture, <hi>Plead with your mother, plead, for she is not my wife, neither am I her husband, let her therefore put away her whoredoms <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ut of her sight, and her adulteries from between her breasts.</hi> Hosea 2.2.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> That a man in Christ doth pray <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd read in the Scriptures.</head>
               <p>THERE is nothing which doeth more move, and unite the affection of a Benefactor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o the party unto which he is bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiall. then the reall, submissive ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment, and hearty sence of benificiency in the party; and his certainly is a figurative spark<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f that im-mense and infinite love-justice <hi>of the King and Lord of love,</hi> shining into, &amp; amongst some men; And there is nothing which is more just and right, then that a
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:170691:11"/> person who lives by the benificien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of a benefactor, should in all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all submissive acknowledgement, &amp; hearty sence, be affected with the love of the benefactor, &amp; this cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly is also a figurative sparkle of that same immense &amp; infinite <hi>Love Justice</hi> of the God of Love, reflect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and manifesting it self to it self, operatively in &amp; among some men.</p>
               <p>Even so there is nothing, which doth more delight, and unite <hi>the God of infinite goodnes, &amp; eternall love,</hi> to a person who through grace be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes an object of his goodnes, &amp; love, then the reall submissive ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement, and hearty sence of his infinite goodnes, and eternall love, in this object, or rather sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject person.</p>
               <p>And there is nothing which is more just and right, then that this subject person, who lives by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite goodnes and eternall love of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170691:11"/> his infinitely good, and eternally loving God, should in all reall sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missive acknowledgment, &amp; hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty sence, be affected with, and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto, this infinite goodnes and eternall love.</p>
               <p>For this manifesteth God, to be God, and the creature to be the creature; God to be infinite good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and eternall love, flowing out of himselfe into this submissive sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible, subject person, as into a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le of the holy Ghost and house of prayer; and flowing again into him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe out of it, the creature to be on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the temple &amp; house, &amp; to be unto God as a house is to a man, that is, God active, &amp; the creature passive.</p>
               <p>This is the true praise which glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>th God; according to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine truth of that Scripture; <hi>Who so o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fereth prayse glorifieth me, and to him that ordereth his conversation aright, will I shew the salvation of the Lord.</hi> Psal. 50.23.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:170691:12"/>
               <p>Thus the Lord obtaineth his own, so that the Crea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ure can give him nothing which is not his own, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the divine truth of that Scripture, <hi>Now therefore our God wee thanke the, &amp; praise thy glorious name, But who am I, and what is my people, that wee should be able to offer so wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly after this sort, for all things come of thee, and of thine own have we gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven thee,</hi> 1. <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.13.14.</p>
               <p>A man in Christ, being baptized into this estate and condition, doth pray, read, &amp;c. and whatsoever he asketh, it is done to him, yea, in him, because he asketh this way truly in the name of Christ? accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the divine truth of that Scripture, <hi>And whatsoever yee shall aske in my name, that will I doe, that the Father may be gloryfied in the son, if ye shall aske any thing in my name, I will do it. Ioh.</hi> 14.13, 14. there is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine reason for this, for a man i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:170691:12"/> Christ, doeth will, and seeke, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther more or lesse, then that which the father in the son, willeth and seeketh in him; the same is to be said, concerning his reading of the Scriptures, &amp; all his godly desires.</p>
               <p>Thus doth a man in Christ seek, and he findeth, he knocketh, and it is opened unto him; he asketh and receiveth. But those, (and oh and alas, the most part of men) who are not baptized into the baptisme of a man in Christ, aske and receive not, bēcause they aske a misse. <hi>Iam.</hi> 4.3. They are like unto hunting <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sau,</hi> mourning for the blessing, &amp; <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon Magus</hi> that would buy Christ, but a man in Christ hath with <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> chosen that good part, which shall not be taken away from him. <hi>Luke</hi> 10.42.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:170691:13"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IIII.</hi> That a man in Christ doth heare the Gospell preached.</head>
               <p>AN honest person, having such a disease, as tendeth to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction of ease and life in pain and weaknes, so that (as he is moved by God) he would use some meanes, for mitigation of pain, and prolonging of life, according to the will of God, and not according to the will of man.</p>
               <p>If this person go out at all to any man of skill, it is certain that it is better to go to such a man, who hath skill in God, then to such as have not their skill in God; now in his thus going our, two things are remark<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>able, first he hath a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all busines which moves him to go, secondly, he goeth to one, in and by whome the cause &amp; remedy of his disease is truly discovered.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:170691:13"/>
               <p>Even so it is with a man in Christ in hearing first he hath a busines of God in his spirit, concerning which he is a captive of God, and panteth after the discovery of it, as the sick person, after the discovery of the cause &amp; remedy of his disease, and even as a fit of sicknes many times doth purge the body, and preventeth a greater sicknesse, yea death it selfe, even so a holy trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the mind, being as it were in an eclipse, maketh thee soule of a man in Christ, the more enamour'd with, and united unto the true eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall light, and in a divine good spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall plight after-wards.</p>
               <p>And even as a sick man discer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the skill of a man, as the man speaketh the very same things, which he knoweth and feeleth in himselfe, or otherwise; even so, a man in Christ, discerneth a true Preacher, that is a true disciple of
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:170691:14"/> Christ, by his own experience; thus doth a man in Christ hēare, not su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perficially, but as a sick man hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a true Physitian, discover the cause, and remedy of his disease, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a divine manner. And as a true Ph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sitian, getteth his skill by the tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> knowledge of diseases, in applying such &amp; such physick unto such and such diseases: Even so a man in <hi>Christ</hi> being an instrumental spiritu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>all physitian, in the hand of the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Physitian, getteth his skill, by the working of God in the soul of his brother; being a man in Christ, aswell as by the working of God in his own soul; And in this divine sence, a man in Christ, although he be a hearer, may upon conference, be a Physian to a man in <hi>Christ,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he be a Preacher according to the divine truth of that Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>For I long to see you, that J may impart unto you some spirituall gift, to
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:170691:14"/> the end you may be established;</hi> that is that I may be comforted together with you, by the mutuall faith both of you and me. Rom. 1.11, 12.</p>
               <p>But it is otherwise amongst hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, who are not men in <hi>Christ,</hi> those that are not in <hi>Christ,</hi> doe go out to the creatures, without the busines we spake of. Some in stead of this busines, go out because it is <hi>Sunday, Sabath,</hi> or <hi>first day,</hi> to heare such a rare <hi>Divine, such a knowing People,</hi> preach and discourse, to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipate <hi>of such and such Ordinances,</hi> &amp;c. Some <hi>to be heard</hi> and <hi>seen</hi> and <hi>applauded</hi> amongst others, <hi>how sweet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly</hi> and <hi>soundly they can tosse a point, what great insight they have in the word,</hi> some <hi>to shew their goodly appar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell,</hi> some to make choise of some <hi>Godly man</hi> (as they call him) <hi>for their husband:</hi> Some <hi>of a woman to be their wife.</hi> But and if these Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons were truly baptized in the bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisme
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170691:15"/> &amp; religion of a man in <hi>Christ</hi> namly, God to be a living active God, in a dead passive ceature, that is, not to move, but as they should be moved by God: they would ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre themselves in dust and ashes, and be convinced by the divine truth of these Scriptures, <hi>Son of man these men have set up their Idols in their hearts, &amp; put the stumbling-block of their iniquity before their faces, should I be inquired of at all by them?</hi> read <hi>Ezek.</hi> 14.3.4.5.6.7.8.</p>
               <p>And again, <hi>But unto the wicked, God saith, what hast thou to doe to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare my Statutes: or that thou should<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est take my covenant into thy mouth, Psal.</hi> 50. <hi>from</hi> 16. <hi>to</hi> 22. And again, <hi>This people draw nigh unto me with their mouth, and honoureth me with their lips, but their hearts are far from me,</hi> Mat. 15.7.8. And again, <hi>Ye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterers &amp;c.</hi> read Jam. 4.4.</p>
               <p>Let those who think that those
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170691:15"/> Sciptures doth nothing at all concern them, take heed lest the God of truth say to them, as <hi>Nathan</hi> said to <hi>David, thou art the man;</hi> Sam. 12.17.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP V.</hi> That a man in Christ, doth some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time speak to his neighbour.</head>
               <p>IF a tender and loving father, who cheerfully and diligently imployeth his strength and calling, for the sustentation and life of his young children, were demanded, why he should do so, seeing that the young children brought no gaines to him, nor profit, he would answer, that fatherly free love moved and constrained him so to doe; even because the weake young children, could neither bring pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit nor gaines to him nor to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves; and that God and nature re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of him so to do, &amp; in so an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swering, he would speak the very
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170691:16"/> truth. Likewise if he were deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded whether or not it were suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent enough for him, that he should go abroad, and look upon food and rayment, and then return to his hungry and naked children, and tell them of such good food &amp; raiment as he had seen, &amp; so satisfy their hunger, and cloath their nakednes with the bare rehearsing of such things, or present painted food, and painted raiment, to satisfy their hunger, and cloath their nakednes.</p>
               <p>He would answer, that there were nothing more rediculous then that question, seeing that his children would be nothing better, although he should let them see food and rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, belonging unto other People without proper use of that food, &amp; that raiment to themselves: much lesse, by the bare telling and speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of food and raiment which he saw abroad, unto them, or shewing
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170691:16"/> the painted formes of food and rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment unto them, which could do them no good.</p>
               <p>He would say, that no lesse would satisfy his children, then the reall use of reall food and raiment, such as God made to be for his own pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation of his life, &amp; in his so an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swering he would likewise speake the very truth.</p>
               <p>Now in the speaking of a man in <hi>Christ</hi> to any person, the spirit of the heavenly father, keepeth this same fatherly nature, so that a man in <hi>Christ</hi> speaketh to the edyfying of any person, who is desirous to heare him, capable in some measure out of meer free love, because the <hi>love of Christ constraineth him,</hi> nor can he do otherwise; for the <hi>Fire</hi> must of necessity send forth <hi>heat,</hi> to those who sit neare it, and the <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle</hi> shine, to those who are where it shineth, according to the divine
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170691:17"/> truth of that Scripture, <hi>Let your light so shine before men, that they see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your good workes may glorify your father which is in Heaven; Mat.</hi> 5.16.</p>
               <p>This in dwelling word of life &amp; love, in a man in Christ is freely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived therefore he freely giveth it, according to the divine truth of that Scripture, <hi>Freely you have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, freely give; Math.</hi> 10.8.</p>
               <p>A man in Christ, thinketh it to be a sweet reward, with which he is fully content to be a dead instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in &amp; by which the God of life motion, action, and eternall love: exerciseth pure and meer goodnes towards any of his creatures.</p>
               <p>This is the reward, which the <hi>sun</hi> in shining the <hi>aire</hi> in <hi>moistning,</hi> the <hi>water</hi> in <hi>watering,</hi> and the earth in <hi>production,</hi> have, and desire to have no other reward; the same is to be said of the whole university of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, set man, as man aside.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:170691:17"/>
               <p>And so speaketh &amp; doeth a man in <hi>Christ</hi> to his neighbour, that is any tractable person, without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception; but those who are not bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tised into a living active God, and dead passive creature, with a man in <hi>Christ,</hi> and yet will take upon them to be leaders of the blind, are those unto whom God and truth, inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their good, directeth these Scriptures, (understand here, aswell a disputant of this world, being a talkative person amongst others, and persons whoever they be, he or she, who hath a form of godlinesse without the power thereof; as a publique <hi>Preaching man,</hi> being a false Prophet) <hi>For when for the time ye ought to be teachers, yee have need that one teach you again, which be the first principles of the Oracles of God,</hi> Heb. 5.12. And again, <hi>Son of man prophesy against the</hi> Shepherds of Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, <hi>prophesy and say unto them, thus
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170691:18"/> saith the Lord God unto the</hi> Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds, <hi>wo be unto the shepheards of Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, that doe feed themselves,</hi> Should not the Shepheards feed the flock? <hi>Ye eat the fatt, and cloath you with the wool, ye kill them that are fed, but yee feed not the flocke, Ezech.</hi> 34 2.3.</p>
               <p>Again, a man in <hi>Christ,</hi> his lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage and works are spirit and life, because it is not he that speaketh or doeth, but the spirit of his heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly father, which speaketh and doth in him, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.20. But those who are not baptized into a man in <hi>Christ</hi> his baptisme, and yet will take the Kingdome of Heaven by violence, do weary themselves in an artificiall, historicall and painted Divinity, concerning which God sayeth, when yee come to appeare before me, <hi>Who hath required this at your hands, to tread my Courts;</hi> Isaiah 1 12. Some attaine to much of this Divinity, (as they call it) by the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:170691:18"/> eye, that is by reading the Books of such and such men, othe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s attain to much of it, by the Eare, that is, by hearing this, or that man, or gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring such &amp; such expressions from one another, which they imitate; And others, do attain to much of it by their own conceptions, and self-will interpretations, and this tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to divisions &amp; cooling of love amongst them exceedingly.</p>
               <p>But all of you of this kind, in the meekenes, Gentlenes, and love of <hi>Christ,</hi> heare what his spirit sayth unto you, <hi>Behold ye despisers, and wonder, and perish, for I worke a work in your dayes, a worke which you shall in no wise believe, though a man declare it unto you, Act.</hi> 13.41. But I trust in God that some of you shall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it; and I would to God that all of you, and I, and all mankind, did believe it aright.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:170691:19"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> That a man in Christ, is a true member of the true Church.</head>
               <p>A Man born in one Country, &amp; travelling through other far Countries, shall alwaies find, and see, that the inhabitants of those Countryes do differ nothing from the Inhabitants of that Country wherein he was born, in essence &amp; essentiall properties, either in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable or unreasonable creatures: But that there is a fame-nesse, (so to speak) of essence and essentiall properties, in and amongst all the particular creatures, of every spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies &amp; kind, whereupon th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler may be, brought to admire the Creator, in his travelling amongst Gods creatures in other countries.</p>
               <p>Now there are three things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderable in this Travellers life, the first is, he is no setled dweller, or member of any country, and yet in
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170691:19"/> some sence, he is a member of every Country, in which he hath been, and where he is.</p>
               <p>The second is, as he liveth by the charity of mercifull hearted people who contributeth to the reliefe of his necessity, so he doeth (as it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh him so to do) sometimes contribute to the necessity of a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son being in greater want then he.</p>
               <p>The third is, as he is willing to heare and receive sure and certain knowledge, from well experienced Inhabitants of the country, where he travelleth, so he is willing to communicate what he hath seen, and known in other countries, to them again, or to others who hath not known and seen such things; And so this harmlesse poor Travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, is a beggar to some, and some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time a giver to others, a hearer to some, and sometime a speaker to others.</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:170691:20"/>
               <p>Even so, a man in <hi>Christ,</hi> being a Pilgrim and a Stranger, deare to God. doth find, feel, and see, the internall world in the externall, &amp; beholdeth all created essences, and essentiall propertyes, to issue out, as sparckles and shadowes of the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mense, infinite, and eternall essence <hi>which is God over all,</hi> blessed forever. Whereupon, his soule as oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is powred out upon the head of his Lord, and his body, as the Box is broken; that is, his soule is protended and carryed without the limits of himselfe and becometh a mysticall and spirituall Pilgrim, in and amongst the countries of the internall world, and there are three things considerable, in his happy and divine pilgrimage-life.</p>
               <p>The first is, he is no setled dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler or member, of any country of the externall world, that is, he fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth &amp; seeth a more excellent way
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:170691:20"/> then the most part of professing men do, who are rather setled upon the earth and externall world, that is, upon their own petty and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Idols in the first place, and their own salvations in a mercinary way in the second place, then setled upon Christ; And yet in some sence he is a member of each country, place, or people, as a deare sojour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner where ever he be.</p>
               <p>The second is, as he is travelling amongst Gods creatures, he doth accurately observe and take speciall notice of God working, and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>festing himselfe in some People, &amp; with those he will have most dear and intimate unity of spirit, &amp; will receive their amiable and christian <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>difying word and worke: for it is manifested to him, that it is not they that do so, or speak so to him, but the spirit of their heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which doth and speaketh so
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170691:21"/> to him; therefore in all subjection and lowlinesse of mind, he feeleth God in his love, and heareth God in his light, in and by such, and is so far from thinking it a disparage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to him, to be benefited either in word or worke by them, that with the two Disciples, going to <hi>Emmaus,</hi> his heart burneth within him, and is affected.</p>
               <p>The third thing is, by the divine illuminating light, which leadeth into all truth, he is made very senci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of two things, the first is, that all persons into whom he cannot discern God manifesting himselfe, do stand in need to be brought to know &amp; feel, that either their God must be glorified in them, that is, to work his will &amp; work in them, which is their eternall happinesse, or else they are undone; The other thing is, he is obliged, by the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and heavenly constraint of the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:170691:21"/> operative love of Christ in him, (himselfe being converted and a follower of Christ) to become a <hi>Fisher of men,</hi> that is, to become all right things unto all men, that truth o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God may gain some, according to the divine truth of that Scripture. <hi>For though I be free from all men, ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> have I made my selfe a servant unto all that I might gain the more. And unto the Jewes I became as a Iew, that I might gain the Iewes, to them that are under the law, as under the law, that J might gain them that are under the law, to them that are without law, as without law, (being not without law to God, but under the law to Christ) that J might gain them that are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out law; To the weak I became as weak, that J might gain the weak; J am made all things to all men, that J might by all meanes save some,</hi> 1. Cor. 9.19, 20. So that a man in Christ, is a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of any men in the world, either
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:170691:22"/> in <hi>Christ,</hi> or not in <hi>Christ;</hi> if they be in <hi>Christ,</hi> he will be a subjected, lowly minded Disciple to them, if they be not in <hi>Christ,</hi> he will (as a deare sympathysing and pitifull commiserator) do his uttermost en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours, to do them good, if they would receive it.</p>
               <p>Thus was <hi>Paul</hi> and the Disciples true members of the true <hi>Church,</hi> and thus is a man in <hi>Christ</hi> a true member of the true <hi>Church;</hi> but those who are not baptised with a man in <hi>Christ,</hi> into a living active God, &amp; a dead passive creature, do commonly either make a God of that w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> is but the creature, that is, they thinke all is done if they be a member of such a church, as they thinke salvation belongeth unto, and herein while they doe as they doe (let none thinke here that I speak against the holy order and discipline of the true Church of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170691:22"/> Christ) they are rather like unto young children, who with shels &amp; little stones will imitate a reall buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, then like true members of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ue Church, that is, called out of the world; for the word Church in the Greeke languge, being rightly interpreted, signifieth a calling out.</p>
               <p>Or else, they account nothing of that which God accounteth dearly of, that is, they separate from such poor, sinfull, ignorant, People, as Christ the Lord God of mercy, free grace and love, did never sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from as they doe.</p>
               <p>For although the Lord <hi>Christ</hi> did not stand in need of the most choy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sest Discipline of the creature, to be benefitted thereby, far lesse of their false worships; for then the candle should have given light to the Sun; then man should have been more perfect then his Maker; then the Pot should have framed the Potter;
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:170691:23"/> then the blind should have led the seeing; yet he being the great light, and DAY SPRING, doth shine, to whom? Even to those that sit in the Region and shadow of death and darknes, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.79. He being the Physitian, he healeth whom? Even the sick; according to the divine truth of that Scripture, <hi>And it came to passe, as Jesus sate at meat in the House, behold many Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licans and sinners came and sate downe with him and his Disciples; And when the Pharisees saw it, they sayd unto his. Disciples, why eateth your master with Publicans and sinners? But when Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus heard it, he said unto them, they that be whole need not a Physitian, but they that are sick, but go you and learn what that meaneth,</hi> I will have mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and not sacrifice, <hi>for I am not come to call the</hi> Righteous, <hi>but sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to repentance; Mat.</hi> 9.10.11.12.13.</p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:170691:23"/>
               <p>He being the seeker, he seeketh, whom? Even the lost, according to the divine truth of that Scripture <hi>What man of you having an hundred sheep, if he loose one of them, doth he not leave the ninety nine in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse: and go after that which is lost, untill he find it,</hi> Luke 15.4.</p>
               <p>It is true then, that those who make so little account of the day of small things, that is poor creatures in their ignorance and infirmities <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et ayming at, &amp; professing christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, did never learn so at Christ; it may be some will object and say <hi>Is it not commanded that Saints should come out of Babel, and be separated?</hi> &amp; the like; To which in loue &amp; truth I answer; There are two sorts of Saints, the one reall, and they will separate from nothing except evill and sinne against God; The other nominall, and it is to be feared that they worship that inwardly,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:170691:24"/> from which they thinke they are separated outwardly, according to the divine truth of that Scripture, <hi>Ther is a Generation that are pure in their own eyes, and yet are not washed from their filthynesse,</hi> Pro. 30.12. And againe <hi>And why beholdest thou the moat that is in thy brothers eye, but considerest not the beam that is in thine own eye,</hi> Math 7 3. A true Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelicall Penitent will say here <hi>Lord be mercifull to me a sinner;</hi> but a <hi>proud Pharis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e</hi> will have much to say for himselfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> That a man in Christ useth the world, that is, Being, Life, Sence, Reason, Food, Rayment, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>A Person looking into a look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-glasse, and beholding the image of his face, may be said in the actuall use of the glasse, not to use it; that is, he is taken up with the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:170691:24"/> image, which he seeth in the glasse, and not with the consideration of of the glasse it selfe; and if he consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the glasse it selfe, while he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oldeth his image in it, if he consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it aright, he considereth it with relation to the reflecting and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verberating vertue which it hath in it, to let him see himselfe.</p>
               <p>Even so, a man in Christ, useth all things without which he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not subsist, as a looking glasse, in which he feeleth and seeth God to be the vertue of each of them, as the Being of his own Being, and all Beings else; the Life of his own life, and all lives else; the Sence of his own sence and all sence else? the Reason of his own reason, and all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eason else; the Food of his own food, &amp; all food els, &amp;c. according to the divine truth of that Scripture, <hi>For the invisible things of him, from the creation of the world, are clearly
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:170691:25"/> seen, being understood by the thing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> that are made, even his eternall power and God-head,</hi> Rom. 1.20.</p>
               <p>Againe, look how much a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, looking into a glasse, and see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his image, esteemeth his image inferiour to his face, the cause and substance of his image; even so much doth a man in Christ esteem himselfe, as he is himselfe inferiour to God, the eternall cause and sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance, in being life, sence, reason, food, rayment, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And herein he is like unto a man, who the more he lookes upon the Sun, the more he is dazled and made impotent in his naturall facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of seeing: Or like unto a poor miserable creature, having com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted notorious theft, in his King<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> intrustments, and is in the power and hands of the King, &amp; the King in stead of rigour and justice, useth all clemency, and liberallity to him,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:170691:25"/> receiveth him into his house, giveth him all things good for him.</p>
               <p>Now, by how much this good King is so gracious to him, and he made sensible of it, by so much this man may, and should stand in sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission, and admiration of the King his goodnesse, and his own unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinesse.</p>
               <p>Even so is it with a man in Christ, in the injoyment of necessary things, he thinkes himself unworthy of any goodnesse, and injoyeth only the use of necessary things, as if he used them not, that is, he injoyeth and relisheth the vertue of God, in things meerly necessary. According to the divine truth of that Scripture, <hi>And they that use this world as though they used it not: for the fashion of this world goeth away,</hi> 1 Cor. 7.31.</p>
               <p>But those, who are not baptised with a man in Christ, into a living acting God, and a dead passive crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:170691:26"/> useth the world, that is, being, life, sense, reason, food rayment, &amp;c. as a leacherous, seducing, and vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glorious Whore useth waters and oyntments to beautifie her face, for the satisfying her lustfull desires.</p>
               <p>And as she useth a looking-glasse, in which when shee beholdeth her Image, shee falleth in love with that Image, because she thinketh that that Image, and her face, the substance of that Image is her owne.</p>
               <p>And by how much a man in Christ, ascribeth all the vertue and excellency of created natures to God, as the eternall Fountaine: By so much doe those, who are not in Christ, ascribe to themselves, that is, they satisfie and please their owne carnall concupiscence in the unjust usurpation of those things which are proper to God.</p>
               <p>And herein they are like unto a man, who having committed noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:170691:26"/> theft in the things which was intrusted to him by his King, and is in the power and hands of the King; and the King in stead of rigour and justice, useth all clemency and libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality towards him, receiveth him into his house, giveth him all good things which are necessary for him.</p>
               <p>Now, in stead of standing in submis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion &amp; admiration of the Kings free grace &amp; goodnesse, and his own un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthinesse, he will be king himself, and assume unto himself as his own, the free &amp; lovely conferred mercies of his good King, according to the divine truth of that Scripture. <hi>Let no man deceive you by any meanes, for that day shall not come, except there come a falling away.</hi> First, <hi>And that man of Sin be revealed, the son of perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, who opposeth and exalteth himself above all that is called God, or that is worshipped, for that he as god, sitteth in the Temple of God, shewing himselfe
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:170691:27"/> that he is god,</hi> 2 Thess. 2.3, 4.</p>
               <p>So then, those that are not bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed with a man in Christ, in a living acting God, and a dead passive crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, are in the sight of God &amp; truth no lesse theeves and usurping rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, in being, life, sense, reason, food, rayment, &amp;c. then those who being found guilty by the Jury are in the eyes of the Judge, sitting upon the Bench.</p>
               <p>And in this unjust wickednesse &amp; darknesse, the most part of men, yea, the whole world (set a few men in Christ aside,) lyeth, according to the divine truth of that Scripture, <hi>Wee know that we are of God, and the whole world lieth in wickednesse,</hi> 1 Joh. 5.19.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> That a man in Christ, exerciseth himselfe in a calling.</head>
               <p>THere is a two-fold Calling in peoples outward conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the one is true, the other
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:170691:27"/> false. The true Calling is such a cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, as the holy Lord God of truth putteth into the heart and hand of those who are men in Christ: And the end of this Calling is two-fold.</p>
               <p>First, to doe good unto all, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specially to help the distressed, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be of the houshold of faith, according to the divine truth of that Scripture, <hi>Do good unto all, but espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to those of the houshold of Faith, Gal</hi> 6.10. Or whether they appeare not to be of the houshold of Faith, but meere distressed creatures, whose necessities asketh, according to the divine truth of that Scripture, <hi>Give to him that asketh, and from him that would borrow of thee, turne thou not away,</hi> that is, <hi>Give unto him, if thou be able, and hee bee in meere necessity,</hi> Mat. 5.42.</p>
               <p>Secondly, to supply the meer ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessities of himselfe and his, in regard that they who are not in Christ, will
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:170691:28"/> not doe to him as hee would doe to them; and therefore he is exercised in a Calling by necessity. According to the divine truth of that Scripture, <hi>Provide for things honest in the sight of all men,</hi> Rom. 12.17.</p>
               <p>And this Calling is very deare to God, because it is performed as a sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice to God.</p>
               <p>The false calling, is such a calling, as the covetous, self-loving, and false spirit of error, putteth into the heart and hand of those who are not bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tised with a man in Christ, in a living active God, and a dead passive crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. And this Calling, although it bear the name of a calling amongst the most part of men; yet in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rison of, and respect to, a true Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, may be tearmed a calling, as <hi>Judas</hi> was termed one of the twelve, or as a false prophet may be termed a Prophet. And the end of this cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is two fold also.</p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:170691:28"/>
               <p>First, principally and mainly to covet, love, and seeke his own good, &amp; advantage in al the things he hath to doe with all men, more then the good and advantage of others; and to grumble and fret at the losse of his own good and advantage, in all the things he hath to do with all men. According to the divine truth of that Scripture; <hi>For the desire of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, is the root of all evill, which while some lusted after, they erred from the faith, and pierced themselves thorow with many sorrowes,</hi> 1 Tim. 6.10.</p>
               <p>Secondly, to lay up treasures for themselves upon earth, and with the rich man, to say, <hi>Soule, soule, eat, drinke and be merry;</hi> never consider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, what they are, and whose they are, and who is the true owner of those good things, which they make themselves Lords of; but either with that Epicurean person, which the spirit and wisedome of God calleth
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:170691:29"/> the foole, <hi>which hath said in his heart there is not a God; are all gone out of the way? they are all corrupt,</hi> Psa. 14.3. Or else with <hi>Ananias and Saphira,</hi> they tempt the Spirit of the Lord in keeping away part of the price, that is, they will not forsake all, and sell all to be baptised with a man in Christ, into a living active God, and a dead passive creature, which is that blessed field, in which is hid, and to be found, the all-rich, and all-glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and all-sufficient everlasting pearle, and treasure even Christ, the joy, delight, and well-pleasing of the Father, then which, there is not such a treasure in heaven or earth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> That a man in Christ doth dye, that is, his soule and body are se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated.</head>
               <p>AS there is a vast difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the life of a man in
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:170691:29"/> Christ, and the life of those who are not in Christ, so is there no lesse dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betwixt their deaths.</p>
               <p>A man in Christ, as was said before, is no farther a man in Christ, then the Holy Spirit of Christ is in him, (and if Christ be in him then the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is dead, that is, it is passive <hi>Rom.</hi> 8 10.)</p>
               <p>Now, as Christ is in him, He is as willing, to returne againe into the bosome, (so to speak with reverence of the Immense, &amp; glorious Majesty of the Incomprehensible Creator.) of his heavenly Father God, as his heavenly Father God, was willing to send him into, and set him upon the stage of this externall visible, world, into which and upon which he was set, after that he came from, and out of invisibility and silence, which was and is the mind and will of God.</p>
               <p>To this invisibility and silence, (I
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:170691:30"/> say) is a man in Christ, as willng to go as to live in the externall visible world, because his happy life is led, and lived in this internall, spirituall and invisible silence, that is, hee is dead, and his life is hid with Christ in God, and herein he is like unto a Kings sonne, whose father is pleased to send him to another country, for a certain time to be taught and trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned up in such and such noble exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cises as becommeth the sonne of such a father, now at the end of this cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain time, he is as willing to returne againe to his father, as his father was willing to send him to that Country.</p>
               <p>But those who are not baptised with a man in Christ, in a living ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive God, &amp; a dead passive creature, are unwilling to leave being, life, sense, reason, belly-god-cheer, Mam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon honor, wise, husband, children, friends, &amp;c. because as theeves and
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:170691:30"/> robbers, they do make all those their owne.</p>
               <p>And herein they are like unto a miserably covetous merchant, going with a great summe of gold, to a Fair or Market, thinking to be a great gainer in his traffique, and as he is going, there commeth upon him an armed man, whom he is not able to resist, and demandeth of him his gold, which unlesse he doe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently give, he will presently kill him.</p>
               <p>Now for feare of his life, he will give all his gold: but he doth not give it freely, but because he is terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by and with the feare of death, and thinketh his life sweeter then death, or his gold, although before he came into this strait, his gold was sweeter to him then his life.</p>
               <p>Even so is it with those who are not men in Christ, they doe leave and part with their life, as the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:170691:31"/> giveth his Gold, and if so be they seeme to give it freely, yet this is that they may be Gainers, and get their soules to be saved.</p>
               <p>But the Lord of truth, Christ, saith, <hi>Who loseth his soule,</hi> that is, who is baptised in a living active God, and a dead passive creature, <hi>shall find it, Luk.</hi> 9 24. for the divine baptisme, comprehendeth the chiefest good of the creature in it.</p>
               <p>It is like unto, yea, it is that spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Arke of <hi>Noah,</hi> that is, <hi>Rest,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which, all that are, are preserved, but those that are out of it are mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serable.</p>
               <p>And thus far hath a man in Christ been paralelled with those men, who are Gods Creatures, some whereof, professing Christianity more emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently, then others, and some lesse, and some little or nothing at all, in those duties and practises of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which they doe use to practise.</p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:170691:31"/>
               <p>Now by the guidance of the holy Spirit of the God of truth, wee will endevour to parallel him with the same men in the light of understand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and judgement, concerning the controverted opinions, which are so much in agitation amongst them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> That a man in Christ dearely loveth true understanding, judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and opinions, and yet he is united unto the higher Good.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving formerly compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a man in Christ wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h professing men, in the duties and practise of such performances, as they do usual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly exe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cise themselves into. We will by the vertue of the Spirit of God and truth, compare him with the same m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n in the understandings,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:170691:32"/> judgements, and opinions, which are amongst them.</p>
               <p>It is true, a man in Christ loveth the knowledge of the truth, because the truth is in him; but yet hee is more united and inamoured, in, and with the spirit, life, and will of the truth, then of the notionall contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation of true knowledge.</p>
               <p>And herein he is like unto a deare sonne comming to his father, and speaking this language; O my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther! for so much as you are the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strument, in, and by which God did beget me, educate me, love me, &amp;c. So that I had, or have nothing of my selfe, but what I have received of you, I conceive that I, and all that I have, is yours, and not mine, and that it is just and right, that I and all that I have, should be imployed and live unto you, and according to your heart &amp; will, and not live unto my selfe, and according to mine owne
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:170691:32"/> heart and will, seeing all is yours.</p>
               <p>Therefore, this is the summe of all my desires, ô my father! let me stand and live in the obedience and unity of your will and well-pleasing, for this onely is justice and equity; for whatsoever I desire, or would desire; whatsoever I have or would have; whatsoever I do or would do more then this, commeth of mine owne e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, and although I stand and live in the obedence and unity of your will and wel-pleasing, and not in my will and well-pleasing, I doe no more then that which becommeth a son to doe to his father, by divine Iustice, yea. I doe no more in my kind, then the Oxe which knoweth his owner, and the Asse which knoweth his masters crib in their kind, this lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage now doth wonderfully in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deare, and rejoyce the loving father, that the son is become so sensible of God his goodnesse, and his own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement.</p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:170691:33"/>
               <p>Even just so doth the life and lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of a man in Christ, speake to God alone.</p>
               <p>But those that are not baptised with a man in Christ, into a living act<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve God, and a dead passive crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, are in the knowledge of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and opinions, as they are in the use of being, life, sense, reason, food, raiment, &amp;c. that is, they are more delighted, and exalted in the notionall contemplation of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and opinions, as they make for their owne glory and excellency of knowledge, (as they call it,) that they may sit at the right &amp; left hand of Christ in all eternity, which is all but self and false christianity, then they are delighted in divine obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and self-abhorring, which is the covenant that God by Christ maketh with all true disciples, and is the only true christianity.</p>
               <p>And hereunto they are like unto
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:170691:33"/> a foolish son, comming to his father, and speaking this language, father ô how rich are you, and ô how rich shal I be, seeing I am your son: Now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause I shall obtaine so great riches from you, it is sitting that I should have excellent knowledge of you every way; therefore father I pray you let me take a knife and rip up your belly, that I may know you perfectly how you are within, how your small gutts lye, how your joynts are coupled and the like.</p>
               <p>This language now is so redicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and contrary to reason, nature and truth, that the father will in no wise either approve or yeeld unto it.</p>
               <p>Even just so doth the life and lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of those who are not baptised with a man in Christ, into a living active God, and a dead passive crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, speak to God alone.</p>
               <p>And therefore their clearest know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, is but ignorance of God and
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:170691:34"/> Christ. According to the divine truth of that Scripture, and though I have the gift of prophesie, and understand all misteries, and all knowledge, and have no Charity, that is, not bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tised in a living active God, and a dead passive Creature, <hi>I am nothing,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.2.</p>
               <p>But a man in Christ feareth the Lord, and therefore the secrets of the Lord are with him. <hi>Psal.</hi> 25.14:</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi> That a man in Christ believeth that there is one God, and this God is Vnity in Trinity, and Trinity in Vnity, <hi>That is,</hi> God in Father, Son and Spirit, and Father, Sonne and Spirit, in God.</head>
               <p>O Thou true eternall Light! whose self manifests thy selfe to all those who have any true ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifestation
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:170691:34"/> of thee, even as the Sun, (being a representative sparkle of that immense glorious Light which thou art,) manifesteth it selfe by it self, to all those who have any true <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>anifestation of it. Arise in the lovely Majesty of thy more then excellent splendor, and let the thick misty clouds of sin and ignorance, which stand as a partition wall, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the glory of thy admirable nature and holy God-head, and the blinded eyes of the understandings of thy poore creatures, be dispersed and annihilated: The clouds of sin and ignorance, I say, O most holy Goodnesse, which they themselves, and not thou, have set up as idols in their hearts, &amp; as stumbling blocks before their faces, &amp; loveth darknes rather then thee, the true everlast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Light w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> shineth in the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and the darknesse compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendeth thee not.</p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:170691:35"/>
               <p>A man in Christ, as hee is man, seeth matter of deepe admiration, not onely in the more noble and greater, but also in the meanest and smallest of the creatures which li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth, either in the earth, water, aire, or fire; each particular and indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duall living creature of every spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies and kind, containing in it selfe as in a mysterious little world or creation, the earth, water, aire and fire, in a corporeall composition, and all of them in a vast variety of vertuous faculties and diverse ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations.</p>
               <p>Now if he be dazled here, (&amp; wel may hee be) unto what inutterable and absolute admiration shall he be brought into, in comprehending the incomprehensible, in seeing the invisible, in searching the unsearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, in terminating the infinite and transcendent Creator, who can no more be reached unto, by the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:170691:35"/> his comprehensive ability then the Sunne can be reached unto, by the arme of creature man.</p>
               <p>And this deepe admiration of the creatures, and absolute admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Creator, is caused to him, as hee himselfe is a particular created creature, that is, an Indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duall person, amongst the innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>able and various multitudes of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther creatures, wherein the almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinesse and boundlesse largenesse of the wonderfull Father and Creator appeareth.</p>
               <p>But as he is in Christ, baptised in a living active God, and a dead pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ive creature, that is, translated out of the kingdome of darknesse into the Kingdom of his deare Son; He i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>oyned to the Lord, and one Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit with the Lord, according to the divine truth of that Scripture, but <hi>he that is joyned to the Lord, is one spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17. <hi>And this spirit search<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:170691:36"/> the deepe things of it self, and nothing else,</hi> 1 Cor. 2 10, 11.</p>
               <p>This way he is a fearer of the Lord, <hi>and the secrets of the Lord are with him,</hi> Psal. 25 14. This way God saith within him and to him as he said to <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>raham,</hi> shall I hide from my beloved creature, being baptised in the true name of my infinitely dearely beloved sonne, that thing which I doe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.7. that is, what I am according to the divine truth of that Scripture, <hi>He that hath my Commandements, and keepeth them,</hi> (that is he that is baptised in a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving active God, and a dead passive creature,) <hi>he it is that loveth me, and he that loveth me, shall be loved of my Father, and I will love him, and will manifest my selfe to him,</hi> Joh. 14.21.</p>
               <p>In this divine union, and blessed Baptisme, doth a man in Christ, by Christ truly feele, know and see these two maine things:</p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:170691:36"/>
               <p>First, That this whole visible U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niversity or World, with all, and every part of it in its beauty &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, (and O how beautifull and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erfect is it) being adorned with such innumerable and various mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>udes of severall kindes of crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ures, is a visible representation, of he invisible, incomprehensible, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>earchable and infinite Being of all beings, which is <hi>Jehovah,</hi> God the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reator; according to the divine truth of that Scripture: <hi>For the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>visible things of him, from the creation of the world are clearely seene, being understood by the things that are made, even his eternall power and God-head,</hi> Rom 1.20.</p>
               <p>And this whole beautifull and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erfect University, or world, with every individuall part thereof in its formal being and operative faculty <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oth issue and flow out of the Creator, because he is God, (that is,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:170691:37"/> absolute, beautifull, perfect good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse and love,) by a necessity, for goodnesse must doe good, by a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity, and love must extend this goodnesse without it selfe, by a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity, and cannot do otherwise.</p>
               <p>Even as the Sunne doth shine by a necessity, and extendeth its light out of it selfe, to and for the good of all things, which it produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth by a necessity.</p>
               <p>And no man truly feeleth, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and seeth, this eternall power and godhead, of the invisible, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehensible, unsearchable, and infinite power, and godhead by the things that are made, but he that is baptised in a living active God, and a dead passive creature, and that is only a man in Christ.</p>
               <p>Secondly, A man in Christ, doth truly feele, know, and see, that as it is altogether impossible to the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall creature man, as man, to as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:170691:37"/> up, and comprehend the Sun, which cannot be comprehended by man, but it comprehendeth man, that is, it extendeth its light unto, and upon man, and so man may be said to comprehend the Sun.</p>
               <p>Even so, impossible is it to the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall creature man as man, to comprehend the incomprehensible, invisible, unsearchable, and infinite Being of all beings, <hi>which is God o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all, blessed for ever.</hi> Unlesse he should manifest his incomprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siblenesse, invisiblenesse, unsearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ablenesse, and infinitenes, into such a manifestation, as the rationall <hi>crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture man</hi> may be in some measure capable of him.</p>
               <p>Now because amongst the ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall creatures, Father, Son, and Spirit, which Spirit is life, motion, and action, are most sencible and u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited relations, the one whereof manifesteth the other, for a Father
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:170691:38"/> is not a Father without a Son; and a Son is not a son without a Father; and a Spirit, that is, life, motion, &amp; action, is not a spirit without father and son</p>
               <p>Therefore the incomprehensible invisible, unsearchable, and infinite Being of all beings, who is the true cause and author of these relations, in and amongst the rationall crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures doth make out, or manifest himselfe in these three relations; that the rational creature man, may by this meanes be made capable in some measure to comprehend the nature of him, who is the true eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall and essentiall nature of all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted natures &amp; in this he is truly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the father, and eternall Creator.</p>
               <p>And to comprehend the love of him, who is the true eternall and essentiall love of all loves, and in this he is truly called the son.</p>
               <p>And to comprehend the <hi>life,</hi> mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:170691:38"/> and action of him- who is the true, eternall, and essentiall life, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton and action of all lives, motions and actions; and in this he is truly called the holy Spirit.</p>
               <p>Now, as amongst mortall crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, a father is not a father with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a son, so the true eternall and essentiall Nature of all Natures, which is the father, is not the true eternall and essentiall Nature of all natures, without the true eternall and essentiall Love of all loves, which is the Son.</p>
               <p>And as a son is not a son without a father, so the true, eternall and es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentiall love of all loves, which is the son, is not the true eternall, and essentiall love of all loves, without the true eternall, &amp; essentiall nature of all natures, which is the Father.</p>
               <p>And as a Spirit which is life mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and action, is not a Spirit, without Father and Son; so the true
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:170691:39"/> eternall &amp; essentiall life, motion, &amp; action, of all lives, motions; and actions, which is the holy spirit, is not the true eternall and essentiall life, motion and action of all lives, motions, and actions, without the true eternall, and essentiall nature of all natures, which is the Father, &amp; and the true eternall and essentiall love of all loves, which is the Son.</p>
               <p>So then, the incomprehensible, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>visible, unsearchable and infinite Power and God-Head is manfest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the capacity of the rationall <hi>creature man,</hi> into <hi>Father, Son, and Spirit;</hi> which three Relative ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifestations, are unto the incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehensible, invisible, unsearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and infinite power and God-head, as the externall written word is unto the internall Spirit and life, unto which the externall written word is a testimony; according to the divine truth of that Scripture
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:170691:39"/>
                  <hi>Search the Scriptures, for in them yee think to have eternall life, and they are they that testify of me,</hi> Joh. 5.39.</p>
               <p>Even so, this threefold manifesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is a testimony of the incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehensible, invisible, unsearchable and infinite eternall power, and God-head, according to the divine truth of that Scripture, <hi>There are three that bear Record in Heaven,</hi> that is, of this incomprehensible, invisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, unsearchable and infinite eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall power and God head, <hi>the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;</hi> the Word, that is the <hi>Son,</hi> and the <hi>holy Spirit, &amp; these three are one,</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Ioh. 5.7.</p>
               <p>Now by these last words, <hi>These three are one,</hi> is holden out, <hi>That as God is unity in Trinity,</hi> that is, <hi>God in Father, Son and Spirit, So</hi> God <hi>is Trinity in unity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And here shineth, as the bright <hi>Sun,</hi> amongst <hi>Moon and Starres, THAT GLORIƲS MYS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TERY
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:170691:40"/> of all MYSTERIES,</hi> namely, as the Father is in the Son, so the Son is in the Father; accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the divine truth of that Scripture, <hi>That they all may be on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> as thou father art in me, and I in the,</hi> Ioh. 17.21. And again, <hi>Beleeve me, that J am in the Father, and the Father in me.</hi> Ioh. 14.11.</p>
               <p>And as the Father and the Son are in the holy Spirit; so the holy Spirit is in the Father and the Son; Even as the heat which floweth out of the essentiall Fire, acting upon a combustible matter; as the Fire is in the Heat, otherwise it should not be heat: so that Heat is in the Fire, otherwise it should not be heate, that is motion, and action of the essentiall Fire, acting upon a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bustible matter; according to the divine truth of that Scripture, <hi>And hereby wee know that he abideth in us, by the Spirit that he hath given us,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:170691:40"/> Joh.</hi> 3.24. And again, <hi>For what man knoweth the things of a man, save the Spirit of a man which is in him, even so the things of God knoweth no man, but the Spirit of God,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.11.</p>
               <p>So then, as the incomprehensible invisible, unsearchable, and infinite eternall power and Godhead, is for the capacity of the rationall crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-man, manifested into unity in Trinity; that is, God in Father, Son, &amp; holy Spirit, So he is Trinity in unity, that is, Father, Son, &amp; Spirit in God; according to the divine truth of that Scripture, <hi>These three are one,</hi> 1. Ioh. 5.7.</p>
               <p>And as no man truly feeleth knoweth and seeth the eternall, power and Godhead, of the incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehensible, invisible, unsearchable and infinite God, by the things th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t are made, except a man in Christ: so there is no man that truly feeleth knoweth, and seeth, the true miste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:170691:41"/> manifestaton of one God, to to be unity in Trinity; That is God in Father, Son, and Spirit and Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity in Unity; that is, Father, Son, and Spirit, in God, Except a man in Christ.</p>
               <p>All others, that is, who are not baptised with a man in Christ, in a living active God, and a dead pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sive creature, do make Idols of the creatures and a monster of the God of the creatures; according to the divine truth of these Scriptures, <hi>Who changed the truth of God into a lye, and worshipped and served the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture more then the Creator, who is bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed for ever, Amen,</hi> Rom. 1.25. And again, <hi>They have set up a King, but not by me, they have made Princes, &amp; J knew it not; of their silver &amp; their gold have they made them Idols,</hi> Hos. 8.4. <hi>Let the wicked forsake his way, and the unrighteous man his thoughts, and let him return unto the Lord, and
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:170691:41"/> he will have mercy upon him: and to our God, for he will abundantly pardon; For my thoughts are not your thoughts neither are your wayes my wayes, saith the Lord; for as the Heavens are higher then the earth, so are my wayes higher then your waies, &amp; my thoughts then your thoughts,</hi> Isaiah 55.7. The meaning of which words, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to God and truth, are to be interpreted thus.</p>
               <p>Let no wicked and unrighteous man; that is, who is not baptised in a living active God, and a dead passive creature, think, that he can more possibly conceive aright of, or be united to God, who is Unity in Trinity, and Trinity in Unity, then it is possible to him, being a heavy earthy creature; to jump up thorow the heavenly Skie; But if he forsake his own way &amp; his own thoughts, that is, if he be baptised in a living active God, and a dead passive crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:170691:42"/> then he getteth the mercy and grace, to feele, know and see in truth and union, this MYSTERY, which no man knoweth; or can know, but a man in Christ.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XII.</hi> That a man in Christ, is baptised in the name of the Father, Son, and holy Spirit, and believeth that this only, and no other, is the true baptisme.</head>
               <p>A Regenerate man in Christ, in his spirituall life, may be tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly compared to a generate man in his naturall life; concerning which naturall man, observe these three things; The first is his generation, and by his Father. Without w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> he can neither be a nursed child or a ripe strong man. The second is, his education, that is, his nursed condition, and this is an act of love, acted by the generator, upon the
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:170691:42"/> generated, to the advancement of the generated, unto his ripe age and strength of body, without w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> he cannot be a ripe strong man, &amp; this education is the end of genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>The third is, his mature corrobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, that is his ripe age and strength of body; and this mature coroboration, is the end of his edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</p>
               <p>Even so, (if we may speak of the truths &amp; holy mysteries of God, by way of similitudes) is <hi>a man in Christ</hi> baptised in the name of the Father, Son and holy Spirit; and seeing it is of concernment to speak in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, how a man in Christ is bapti- in each of these three names.</p>
               <p>O thou true Father, and eternal author of divine Generation! Without whose lovely drawing no man can come unto, or know the Son Christ, and holy Spirit; let the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:170691:43"/> lively influence of thy divine light, and quickning vertue, be a testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and unerring guide, to discover to thy poor creatures, how a man in Christ is baptised in thy name.</p>
               <p>A man before he be in Christ, is first, like unto, yea he is that man who neither is, or hath any thing of himselfe, neither body or mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, neither soule or faculties, but is a meer absolute created nature made by the Creator, who is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect goodnes and love; according to the divine truth of that Scripture; <hi>Cease you from man whose breath is in his nostrils, for wherein is he to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted of</hi> Isaiah 2.22.</p>
               <p>Secondly, he is like unto, yea he is that man of sin, who opposeth &amp; exalteth himselfe above all that is called God; 2. Thes. 2.4. that is, he calleth and accounteth light dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and darknes light, all that he doeth is better then that which ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:170691:43"/> God or Gods People doth; In his own estimation he is the only thing that is best: and ought to be loved and honoured; If he be made a God by any creature, that is, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured, loved, reverenced; and yet his own will and delight satisfyed, he rejoyceth exceedingly, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a God of that creature, for no other end, but that that creature should make a God of him in every thing, wherein he desireth, to be made a God of; And so he runneth on in this his fierce and deluded course; Either with the Prodigall Son, <hi>in the lust of the eye, in the lust of the fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>sh, and pride of life;</hi> Or in a burning zeal with <hi>Saul,</hi> breathing out threatnings and slaughter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Disciples of the Lord; Or in hypocrisie with <hi>Jehu,</hi> and the Pharisees. But now, whil'st this poor mad, deluded creature, (who afterwards by grace becometh a
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:170691:44"/> man in Christ) is posting on in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and iniquity, there cometh some certain happy moment of time, in the which it is with the soul of him as it is with a young Woman, which in a naturall way is wounded and ravished with the love of a comely and proper man, so that there is a holy flame and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine extasie ingendred, and this soule is exercised with some un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>speakeable lovely agony, and yet it cannot well tell, what is the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with it; and here there is a voice which in majesty, spirit, and life, calleth and saith, <hi>stand sinner,</hi> and this word <hi>stand,</hi> is the eternall word of the Father, saying, <hi>let there be light in the Micro-chaos,</hi> that is, in the sinner possessed with this dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and iniquity, and there is light; Whereupon is straight presented unto this POOR SOUL its own great misery, and its fathers great
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:170691:44"/> mercy; its own abounding sin, and its Fathers superabounding grace; here is presented Heaven and Hell; here is joy and sorrow; here is fire and wax; here is the sinner (like <hi>Saul</hi>) smitten [blind] down to the ground, hearing this sound, <hi>sinner, sinner, why persecutest thou me?</hi> Here is the sence of the swinish food: &amp; the sence of the fathers House; In short, here is such a work in this new foundation: as no man can speak, or think of aright, but only he that hath felt it.</p>
               <p>Now as every thing which is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest &amp; produced, tendeth toward its own first matter, and principle again: even so this divine funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall manifestation of the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall light, beginneth to tend to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards it selfe, so that the yeelding soule incordiall love, beginneth with halting <hi>Jacob,</hi> tongue ty'd <hi>Moses,</hi> and blind <hi>Saul,</hi> to say, what
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:170691:45"/> is thy Name? And who art-thou ô Lord? And in this question, (ō ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration!) a certain divine know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge desiring to know, asketh this question. To which in cordiall love is answered, I am the Father, and thy Father, that is, the true eternall Nature of all Natures; all created natures are mine, which are in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, earth, and Sea, and by them my eternall power and Godhead, should be understood; by my ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall creature man; upon whom I have bestowed more Donations &amp; indowments; then unto all other inferiour Creatures, which live ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the earth water, ayre or fire; and all the created natures of my u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niversall world, abideth in their first estate of their creation; that is, they are all very good, and no way repugnant to my will; that is they call no vertue or faculty which is performed in any of them, their
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:170691:45"/> own: nor do they exalt or admire themselves in these donations and indowments, which I have given them, but every one of them spend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and changeing themselves for the good of another; as if (and it is most true) they were not created for themselves, or for their own good, but for the good of another.</p>
               <p>This is my will, in this I am glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifyed, in this I am manifested to be the Creator: and the w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e of my hands to be the creature; In this all my creatures are and have nothing in themselves, and are and have all, and whatsoever they are and have in me; Thus I fill the heaven, earth, water, ayre and fire, with my good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes; Thus I AM THE LORD, and there is none beside me, <hi>and my glory will I not give to another.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But now, ō thou my reasonable creature man! In whom my eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall power &amp; Godhead, should &amp;
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:170691:46"/> ought to have been most conspicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously manifested; thou who should have been amongst other inferiour creatures, as the Moon, yea, the Sun amongst the Starres, as my more noble and more excellent creature who as thou art my creature-man, I have made as a sustemm, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend of the whole visible world, containing in thy selfe the Being, Vegitation and Sences of all inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our crea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>es; And moreover, out of my Fatherly wel-pleasing Will, have crowned thee with the divine faculties of an immortall and ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Spirit, that thou shouldest un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand, feel, know, and see my e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall power and Godhead, by the things that are made; that is, the creatures; and that thou shouldest (in a more noble &amp; excellent man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, by how much I have made the a more noble &amp; excellent creature, then all the inferiour creatures)
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:170691:46"/> have bidden in me, and have been no way repugnant to my will; that is not to thinke and call any thing thine own, whether body or soule, or any thing that belongs to either, nor to have exalted and admired thy selfe, in whatsoever thou art or hath; for whatsoever thou essen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially art or hath, is mine and not thine; but with the same ayre, wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, earth, candle, and all other ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rationall creatures, to have been for the good of others, and not for thy selfe; thou that shouldest have been the mirrour of all the irrationall creatures, even thou art most irra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall, yea, thou art worse then irrationall, for thou art ante-father, that is, against me God the Father, thou wilt be something thy selfe, yea, thou wilt be the father thy selfe thou wilt exalt &amp; admire thy selfe, thou wilt be mainly for thy own proper selfe, and selfe-good; thus
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:170691:47"/> thou art against my will, thus thou derogates from my glory, thus am I not manifested to be the Creator, and thou the creature; thus I am not all, and thou nothing; thus I am not the Lord, but there is some besides me; thus my glory is fello<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niously usurped by another, and I appeall to thy own understanding, &amp; conscience, whether it be so or not.</p>
               <p>Now the yeelding soule, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come by the authority of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his answer, making the soule in some measure capable of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly nature, weepeth through joy and rejoyceth through mourning, and uttereth this language.</p>
               <p>O Father and fountaine of pure goodnes, love and truth; I am o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome, O I am overcome, and convinced; O what wilt thou doe with me, who have been a horrible Rebell against thy fatherly good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:170691:47"/> love and truth, who have set my selfe in thy seat, and made my selfe my God; O what Hell is suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to revenge thy divine justice upon me? But alas! Why say I so? I feel, know and see now by thy most holy, and pure truth, that my disobedience to thy divine will is the cause and evill of Hell, Oh that I had never been born to my selfe, Oh what shal I doe, Oh mercy, mercy.</p>
               <p>And thus is this soul brought into a holy agony, and divine indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and desperation against it selfe, so that it abhorreth sinfull selfe, &amp; sweetly embraceth holy truth; and thus, it is baptised in the name of the Father; thus the Father draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to thee Son, and this is the first divine generation, without which none is, or can be rightly stated in the true filiation, or nursed condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of divine education.</p>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:170691:48"/>
               <p>Now as the new born infant, when it commeth into this world, standeth in an absolute necessity of food &amp; yet of it selfe can neither think, speak, or perform any meanes for its food, but lives by, and upon the food which the tender hearted and loving Parent nurse feedeth it withall, as an impotent passive creature.</p>
               <p>Even so, a new regenerated child of God, wakened and raysed up out of sin and ignorance, by the lovely Majesty, and over-coming truth of the Father; And seeing the Father to be the true owner &amp; possessour of all things spirituall &amp; earthly; and the creature to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, of and by it selfe; doth now feel, know, and see an absolute ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity, to be baptised in the name of the Father, that is, to let the Father have his own will in all things, and in all conditions; But
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:170691:48"/> now by the vertue of this divine BAPTISME, he feeling, knowing an seeing in himselfe, the Diabolicall selfe seeking, and self-loving power, or rather impoten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and delusion of the old Serpent, creature man; He doth likewise feele, know, and see, that of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe he can neither thinke, speake, or use any meanes, for the manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his new regenerated baptis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me; And therefore the true eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall nature of all natures, even the father, in whose selfe and name he is now regenerated and baptised becometh unto him the true eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall love of all loves, that is Iesus Christ, to be his nursing Saviour, and teaching Master, who for his sake, AND ALL TRUE PENITENT SINNERS that they might be of his mind, and made capable in some measure of his ETERNALL LOVE,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:170691:49"/> made himselfe of no reputation, &amp; tooke upon him the forme of a ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, and was made in the likenesse of man, and being found in fashion as a man, he humbled himselfe, &amp; became obedient unto death, even he death of the Crosse, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.7.</p>
               <p>And again, the soul being re-born and baptised in the name of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, becometh a dearly beloved child, and Disciple of Iesus Christ; unto whom all power that is in heaven &amp; earth is given, as he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth himselfe, <hi>Math.</hi> 28.18. Here now is his Anchoring-place, betwixt the absolute necessity on the one, hand, and the absolute im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possibility on the other hand.</p>
               <p>And here, as the loving nursing Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent is delighted in feeding &amp; educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the child: &amp; as the child is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amor'd &amp; delighted in the feeding upon, and educating of the Parent,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:170691:49"/> by the substance &amp; vertue of whose flesh, and bones, the child liveth; Even so, <hi>Jesus Christ,</hi> the true, eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall lovely son, and love it selfe, is delighted and rejoyced in spirit, when the sonne, which no man knoweth but the Father, and the Father which no man knoweth but the Sonne, is revealed unto regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate babes <hi>Luke</hi> 10.21, 22. and again regenerate babes, <hi>eating the flesh and drinking the bloud, John.</hi> 6.54. that is, feeding upon Christ, <hi>are members of his body, of his flesh, and of his bones,</hi> Ephe. 5.30.</p>
               <p>But now as it is natural to a child, who is dearly beloved and carefully nursed by the parent, to grow pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumptuous, by the indulgency of the parent and extravagant in plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing its own humours and phancy, as to jumpe out of the armes of the parent into the fire or water, or to affect things which are not good
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:170691:50"/> for it selfe, and as it is naturall to the wise loving parent to moderate in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgency and in wisdome and love to restraine extravagancy.</p>
               <p>Even so it is incident to a regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate babe in Christ, to grow exalted above moderate measure, through the abundance of light and love, and extravagant in its desires, and affections to satisfie its own selfe in spirituall selfinesse.</p>
               <p>But Iesus Christ the Annointed Saviour of his people, and true mortifier of all selfinesse, and exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of flesh and spirit in them, as he is the nurse he feedeth, and as he is the master, he teacheth his owne deare child and disciple after this manner.</p>
               <p>O thou the object and subject of the secrets and true light of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther! O thou the object and subject of my love! who am one with the Father, and in the Father, and the
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:170691:50"/> Father in me! Wouldest thou walk worthy of thy Father, who hath made thee his owne deare child and son, by grace and favour? Wouldest thou walk worthy of thy son-ship and high calling? Wouldest thou be truly filiated, and make the calling and election of thy divine regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and baptisme in the name of the father sure.</p>
               <p>Then looke unto me &amp; my love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly life, who for thy sake and restau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, that thou mightest be bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed in the external love of the father which is in my name, and that the same mind should be in thee which was also in mee, although I being the brightness of the father his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and the expresse Image of his person, and upholding all things by the word of my power. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I being in the forme of God thought it not robbery to be equall with God. Yet made my selfe of no
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:170691:51"/> reputation, and tooke upon me the forme of a servant, and was made in the Likenesse of man, and being found in fashion as a man, I humb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led my selfe, and became obedient unto death, even the death of the crosse, holding and pointing out unto thee and all true children and Disciples, that as none can come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me except the father draw him, so no man commeth to the father but by me.</p>
               <p>So that the eternall love of and to the Father, must overcome, Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie, neglect, and annihilate, all self-love and exaltation, whether in Temporall or Spirituall.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And shall the disciple be above his master? shall I make my self of no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, according to my lovely will which is the will of the father, and shall my disciple bee great in reputation? shall I in assuming a mysterious person like unto, and in fashion as a man, be as
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:170691:51"/> it were a shaddow in my outward man, in the visible world,</hi> Though the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat and full substance of the invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible world in my inward man, and shall my disciple be great in the visi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble world, in rejoycing in, or united unto, any thing in it? Shall I be humbled and my disciple exalted? Shall I become obedient unto the death, even the death of the Crosse; and shall my disciple have gloriati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and pleasure? Shall my gloriati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and divine pleasure, be onely in the resignation and selfe deniall of resignation and selfe-denyall? And shall my disciple live in <hi>non</hi>-resig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and selfness? Shall I be poor, and my disciple rich? Shal I mourn, through the sense of the sinnes of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and shall my disciple laugh, being unsensible of his owne sinne? Shall my Crowne bee in the holy Crosse, and shall my disciple have his crowne in lying vanities? Shall
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:170691:52"/> I as a Mysterious Man, and Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer of man, bee nothing in my Manhood, and shall my disciple be somthing in himself &amp; manhood? <hi>Shall the Foxes have holes, and the birds nests, but I have nothing wherup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to lay my head;</hi> and shall my disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple have any thing to lay his head upon? Shall I come not to do my owne will; and shall my disciple do his owne-will? Shall I be dead and passive, and shall my disciple be alive and active?</p>
               <p>Now the regenerate soule being illuminated and baptised before in the name of the father, becometh no lesse inamoured, indeared, and affected with this holy and heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly life, of the sweet and lovely Lord God Christ, then it was with the blessed and joyfull illiumination of the Father of lights, and so is bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed in the name of the sonne, and becommeth separated and transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:170691:52"/> out of the kingdome and ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of its owne self-something, selfe love, and selfe-will, into the kingdom and element of the father his selfe-all-nesse, his selfe-love, and his selfe-will,</p>
               <p>And this true divine food and discipline, being sweetly and kindly rellished, and in a divine manner (so to speak, &amp; the Spirit of God spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth so in the Scripture) made the flesh and bones of the soule and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, causeth the life and language of this dearly Beloved Babe-disciple, to utter and expresse it selfe even in such a likenesse &amp; sweet same-nesse of mind with Christ, as there is a likenesse and similitude, betwixt the natural nursing parent, and the nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed child.</p>
               <p>So that the same mind is in it, which was also in Christ, and this divine education of Christ, is to be truly baptised in his Name, which
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:170691:53"/> baptisme is the end of being regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated of the Father, and without which none is, or can be baptised in the Name of the Holy Spirit.</p>
               <p>Now as the child first generated, and afterwards nursed and fed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth an able strong person, to be imployed in and about the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires and businesses of his parents; even so a man in Christ baptised in the Name of the Father, that is, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generated of and by the Father, and baptised in the Name of the Sonne, that is, educated and nursed up in the life &amp; love of, and to the Father alone, becommeth to bee an able strong person, (in comparison of meere creature man) in, and about the affaires and businesses of the Father and Son.</p>
               <p>So that hee is no more now for himself, but for the good of others, he that was before the object of at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance &amp; education, becommeth
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:170691:53"/> now an attendant and educating instrument to attend, and educate o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. He that was in the way of strengthning before, is now become the strengthener of others, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the divine truth of that Scripture, <hi>therefore when thou art con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, strengthen thy brethren.</hi> Luke 22.32. though he bee free from all men, yet he becommeth now a ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant unto all, that he may win the more, hee becommeth unto the Jewes as a Jew, that he may winne the Jewes, to them that are under the Law, as though he were under the Law, that he may winne them that are under the Law. To them that are without Law, as though he were without Law, (when he is not without Law as petaining to God; but is in the Law through Christ.) That he may win them that are without Law. To the weak he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth as weak, that he may win
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:170691:54"/> the weak. He is made all things to all men, that he may by all meanes save some According to the divine truth of that Scripture, which w<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> cited in the sixth Section.</p>
               <p>And thus is he baptised in the Name of the holy Spirit, which is the end of his being baptised, in the Name of the Son, as his being bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tised in the Name of the Son is the end of his being borne of, and bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tised in the Name of the Father.</p>
               <p>But those that with a man in Christ, are not baptised in a living active God, and a dead passive crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, are deluded and deceived, in their being baptised in each of those three Names, for first the false light of the false father deceiveth them, that is, they will not let the true Father have his fatherly preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive in them, but they will appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priate, will, love, possesse, and act something themselves. Secondly,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:170691:54"/> the false love of the false christ de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveth them, that is, they love themselves better then the Father. Thirdly, the false life of the false spirit deceiveth them, that is, they doe not love their neighbour as themselves.</p>
               <p>And albeit, there be many and diverse Religions and Baptismes amongst many and diverse people of the habitable world: yet to be baptised with a man in Christ, truly and essentially in the Name of the Father, Son, &amp; Holy Spirit, is only the best; all others are not the best.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIII.</hi> That a man in Christ, hath his eternall well-being in Christ, and believeth that all men in whom Christ is, and they in Christ, have their eternal wel-being in Christ.</head>
               <p>AS the members of the body, and branches of the tree, have
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:170691:55"/> their originall being in the body and tree, but their operative welbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the spirit and life of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and tree.</p>
               <p>Even so a man in Christ hath his originall being in God, but his ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative well being in the spirit &amp; life of his God: So that albeit a man in Christ, doth feele, know, and see his being in the being of all beings. which is his God and Creator, (and O how unspeakeably good is it to feele know, and see it so) yet is his chiefe felicity not altogether placed in his originall being, but in his ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative welbeing: that is, in the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and life of his God and Saviour.</p>
               <p>It is his ioy and his crowne, to be acted as a dead passive creature, in &amp; by the Spirit of God, as the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the body and branches of the tree, which are dead and passive in themselves, and have no motion, action, or fruitfulnesse, but what
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:170691:55"/> motion, action, and fruitfulnesse, they have in, and by the Spirit and life of the body and tree.</p>
               <p>Thus his salvation and eternall well-being is wrought in him by the spirit and life of his God, who is the only worker of it, according to the divine truth of that Scripture, <hi>Workout your own salvation with fear and trembling, for it is God which wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in you both to will and to do of his good pleasure,</hi> Phil. 2.13.</p>
               <p>Now as a man in Christ being baptised in a living active God, and a dead passive creature, hath his eternall well-being in his head and Lord Christ, who saves him with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out himselfe, yet in himselfe; even so hee beleeveth that all men in Christ thorow the whole world, of what Nation or people soever they be, have their eternall well-being in Christ, according to the divine truth of that Scripture; <hi>Then Peter
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:170691:56"/> opened his mouth and said, Of a truth I perceive that God is no respecter of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, but in every Nation he that fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth him and worketh righteousnesse;</hi> that is, he that is baptised in a living active God, &amp; a dead passive crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, is accepted with him, <hi>Ast.</hi> 10.34, 35.</p>
               <p>But he beleeveth, (and it is most true) that al men thorow the whole world, of what Nation or people soever they be, that are not in Christ and Christ in them, although they have their originall being in God, that is, although there being, life, senses, reason, and the like, doe all belong to God, the true being of all beings, the true life of all lives, the true sense of all senses, the true rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of all reasons: Yet unlesse their being, life, senses, reason, and the like be unto God, as the members of the body, and branches of the tree, (which are the organs or instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:170691:56"/> in and by which the spirit and life of the body acteth. Its spirit and life-operation, and the spirit &amp; life of the tree, acteth its spirituall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>egitation and fruitfulnesse) are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o the body and tree; they have not their operative welbeing in God. The reason is, that their operative being unto God, as the members ate unto the body, and the branches unto the tree, is their only best, and eternal welbeing. This is the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and divine light of a man in Christ, touching the point called generall <hi>Redemption,</hi> which is so much agitated amongst some per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, and these not of the meanest note of profession; and therefore they shall do well to take heed with all diligence unto the truth of <hi>Jesus</hi> in this point; for unlesse they be baptised with a man in Christ, in a living active God, and a dead pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sive creature, and so be unto God,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:170691:57"/> as the members are unto the body, and the branches unto the tree, in stead of holding out generall re-Redemption to all others, they may come short of particular Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, that is, eternall welbeing themselves. A man in Christ, <hi>Paul</hi> by name, thought it no disparage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to say so of himselfe, in hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out the Gospell of Christ to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: <hi>But I keepe under my body, and bring it into subjection, lest that by any meanes when I have preached to others, I my selfe should be a cast-way,</hi> 1 Cor. 9.27. And I dare say, that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle was as truly honest, as any in this generation who professeth discipleship.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:170691:57"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIV.</hi> That a man in Christ doth feel, know, and see in himselfe, that as he is a creature, that is, of himself, he can neither will nor do good. But as he is a creature, that is, himselfe, he can both will and doe evill, and the same doth he believe of all other men, as they are creatures, that is, them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves. Againe, as he is in Christ, he doth scele, know, and see in himselfe that he <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>oth can and will doe good through Christ, which strengtheneth him, and cannot in complacency, will and doe evill, and the same doth he believe of all other men in Christ.</head>
               <p>AS a mans hand which is altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther without skil in writing, can neither performe meane writing nor good writing of it selfe, but whilst it is in another hand which is very
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:170691:58"/> skilfull and leadeth it, it can by its owne rude and extravagant motions marre and deface the life and vigour of true writing.</p>
               <p>And as a mans hand w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> is altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther without skil in writing, becomes as it were dead &amp; passive, in the hand of a most skilfull writer, through the vertuous faculty and skil of the lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hand, performeth a caracter and shape of letter, according to the life and vigor of true writing.</p>
               <p>Even so a man in Christ, as he is a creature, that is, as he is himselfe is like unto a hand which is altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther without skil in writing, and can no more will, or act, divine operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, then the rude hand can perform true writing.</p>
               <p>And as the rude hand, although it hath motion and action in it selfe, yet it is so irregular &amp; extravagant in motion, and so be stirring in it selfe whilst it should be redacted into a
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:170691:58"/> cessation &amp; silence in the hand of the most skilfull true writer, that it is so far from true writing, that it impea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth and marreth the true caracter and shape of the letter.</p>
               <p>Even so a man in Christ as he is man and creature, that is, himselfe, is so irregular, and extravagant in all his faculties and operations, that he doth rather impead, and marre di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine operation, then otherwise.</p>
               <p>Againe, as a mans hand which is altogether without skill in writing, becommeth as dead and silent in and to the hand of the skilfull writer, as the pen is dead and silent in and to this same rude hand, although his hand be vnskilfull and ignorant, yet by the leading power and skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full faculty of the hand of the power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and skilfull writer, there is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed such writing, as the master writer is well pleased withall.</p>
               <p>Even so a man in Christ, becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:170691:59"/> as dead and silent in and to God, as the dead and silent pen, is in and to the hand, although he be in himselfe impotent and ignorant, yet he is made to bring forth such fruits in Christ, as is well pleasing to God the Father.</p>
               <p>And here commeth three questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, shortly and briefely to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded and answered.</p>
               <p>The first is, what the leading hand requireth of the hand to be led, whether active motion or pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sive silence.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ans.</hi> Passive silence.</p>
               <p>The second is, what the leading hand affecteth and would be at, when and whilst it is conjoyned with the hand to be led, whether activ<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> motion, or passive silence.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ans.</hi> Active motion.</p>
               <p>The third is, whilst the led hand is agitated, moved and led in the act of writing, whether is it active or passive?</p>
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:170691:59"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ans.</hi> In regard of it selfe, it is passive, in regard of the lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hand, it is active, and therefore it is actively pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sive, and passively active.</p>
               <p>It is even so in the state of life, and judgement of light of a man in Christ, concerning this point called Co-operation, which is so much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitated and controverted in these times.</p>
               <p>Some do too much affect to have the pen write without the hand, and others to have the hand write with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the pen, but none of these is the better way, for Christ the Lord and eternall truth saith, <hi>I in you and you in me, as the branch cannot beare fruit of it selfe, except it abide in the vine, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> more can yee, except you abide in me,</hi> as was cited before in the first Section.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:170691:60"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XV.</hi> That a man in Christ doth fee know, and see in himselfe that Go<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> doth love him, forbid him of evill and offereth mercy and health to his misery, sinfull sicknesse and death, and believeth the same of all others.</head>
               <p>GOd the Father and a man in Christ (if we may speak of the Holy mysteries of God, after the manner of men, and in parables) may be truly compared, as a loving father, who is dearly in love with his owne child and son, which son when he is capable to understand good from evill, the bowell-hearted father labours by all meanes of dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest love to keepe and save from evill, and to advance him in God; now there is a whore-house not far off, and the father well knowing the
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:170691:60"/> pronenesse of the beloved son to be such as may easily be insnared, by the seducing whore, and be not only infected with the contagious and filthy disease which cleaveth unto the whore, and which tendeth to death, but also is grievous and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the fathers heart and will, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presseth &amp; manifesteth his mind and will unto his dearly beloved sonne, in this manner; O my tender and deare sonne, for as much as thou art my son, and hath issued out of my bowels, my will and mind is, that thou shouldest be well and stated in good, that is, that thou shouldest stand and live in my will, as becomes the son of such a loving father, and the standing and living in my will is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hy only best outward welbeing and chiefest good; now my will and mind is, that thou be imployed and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cised, in and about the affaires of my will and mind, and they shal not
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:170691:61"/> bee grievious or burthen some unto thee, for I shall direct and lead thy hand, in every thing which I require of thee, and abstain from the whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>house which my soul abhoreth, there is nothing which is against my will and mind but whoredom, therfore if thou wouldest walke worthy of my love towards thee, if thou wouldest be well, and stated in good; doe not prostitute thy body to an whore, by the infection &amp; contagion of whose filthy disease, thou may be in great danger of (if not lose) thy health of body and life, and ingulfe thy selfe in the element and pit of contrariety to my will, mind, and pleasure.</p>
               <p>Thus I tender my will and mind unto thee, and as the man of God <hi>Moses</hi> said unto the antient peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, so say I unto thee, <hi>I call Heaven &amp; earth to record this day against thee, that I have set before thee life and death,</hi> Deut. 30.19. And I my selfe
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:170691:61"/> will be surety for thy good and wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>being and life in every thing that I require of thee, if so be thou wilt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signe and give up thy selfe to my will and mind, otherwise, neither will I, (nor is it fitting for me to be) bound surety for thy good, health, and life. Now the son although he heare this his fathers divine, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly counsell, yet through the lust of the flesh, and love to please his own humours, he goeth out contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y to his fathers mind and will, in unto the who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, with the young man void of understanding, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold this whore prevailes with him, and hee committing fornication with her, catcheth, and is so misera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly infected with that contagious, and filthy disease, that he loseth the right use of every member of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, his eyes are dimme, his hands, armes, body, feet, and legges are all festered, &amp; becommeth impotent to
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:170691:62"/> every function, and here is he lying, in this his miserable and wretched condition, to the griefe and displea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of his loving Father.</p>
               <p>Now, if any person or persons, should come and lay the cause of the sonnes misery upon the father, they would be grosly in the wrong, and in unjust judgement; for these th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ee things in the father, namely, Love, forbidding of the evil, grief and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleasure, doe vindicate the pious loving father, from all such asperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of men, yea, he commeth to the son whilst he is in this woful plight, and expresseth himself in this maner. O my sonne! What hast thou done? where art thou? hast thou endevour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to kill thy selfe, by rejecting my lovely mind and will, and running into that horrid &amp; detestable life, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroying whordom, which I so care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully in my love forbad thee of? O how am I grieved for thee my son?
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:170691:62"/> notwithstanding although thou hast left off to be my sonne, yet I remain thy loving Father.</p>
               <p>Wilt thou be made whole? I can cure thee sufficiently and truly.</p>
               <p>And here am I as ready and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to cure thy misery, as I was care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to forbid thee to run into it, and as I promised my selfe to be surety for thy good and welbeing, if thou hadest remained in my mind and will, so now I promise my selfe to be security for thy recovery and health, if thou, as a subjected patient wilt resigne and give up thy selfe to my will and minde, in thy cure.</p>
               <p>And my mind and will is that I shall give, &amp; thou shalt receive these two things; the first is a corrasive which must eate out, and consume all the putrifaction, and invenum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed humors of thy infected flesh, and this corrasive in regard of thy vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment disease, may, yea, will seem at
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:170691:63"/> the first more bitter and painfull to thee, then the disease it selfe. But not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding, thou must by an abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute necessity have this same in the fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>st place, otherwise it is impossible for thee to recover health and enjoy life.</p>
               <p>The second is, a comfortable plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant cordiall of a healthfull nature, which must by its vertue give vigor and strength, to the restoring of thee into thy well-being and confi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>med estate.</p>
               <p>Now the son must be considered two wayes, first, either he su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ject<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th himself to the health-giving Father physitian, or else hee rejecteth his fathers offer and his owne recovery.</p>
               <p>If in obeying his Fathers will and mind he subject and resigne him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe up into the hands of the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving father, then he expresseth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe after this manner.</p>
               <p>O Father I have sinned against hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:170691:63"/> and before thee, and the sin is more bitter unto my soule, then thy corrasive is or wil be unto my body, therfore welcome corrasive, into thy hands O father, I commit my self to be dealt withall according to thy will and mind, be the corrasive how it will!</p>
               <p>And O what unspeakable and fatherly inward bowels and delight is there in the father here, to see the lost son in the way of finding! there are not only hopes, but certainty here, through the goodnesse of all good, that this sick patient shal both stand in his recovered health, and in the will and mind of his owne fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther againe.</p>
               <p>But if in rejecting and disobeying his fathers will and mind here, hee will not submit and resigne him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe up into the hands of h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s saving father, then he expresseth himselfe after this manner.</p>
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:170691:64"/>
               <p>Father, I do greatly desire to be recovered, although I be not in great fear of my life, but if that cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rasive which you speak of be more bitter and painfull to mee then my disease it self, I had rather be as I am, yet this I wil do, if you wil be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to heale me by the comfortable pleasant Cordiall, I wil commit my selfe into your hands, but as for the sharpe and painfull corrasive, I will not meddle with it.</p>
               <p>Here is the father no lesse grieved and offended for the sons rejecting, resisting, and refusing his cure, then his running into the disease.</p>
               <p>And this disease doth more and more tend to the debility and death of this selfe willed and froward pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, concerning whom, commeth these three questions, briefly to be propounded and answered.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The first is, what is the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test outward misery of this infected person?</p>
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:170691:64"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ans.</hi> The want of good, that is, not to stand in his fathers will and mind, nor to enjoy sound health and true use of members, senses, and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, and the having of evil, that is, to stand in his owne will and mind, and to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy, or rather to be insor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed and dye into every evill that is contrary to good.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The second is, who is the cause of this evill, misery, and death of this infected person, whether the father or the son himselfe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ans.</hi> The sonne himselfe, by his owne selfe-will and mind:</p>
               <p n="3">3. The third is, whether the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be not as ready to give health to this infected dyin<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> person, as he was willing t<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> forbid the evill of his infe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ction?</p>
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:170691:65"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ans.</hi> Certainely he is: And the same is to be said concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning God &amp; creature man, as God hath manifested himselfe clearely in the Scriptures, in which these three things.</p>
               <p>Namely, Love, forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of sinne, and (so to speake of God, and hee speaks so of himselfe in the Scripture) griefe, (not only for the infectious sin of the creature, but also for the creatures rejecting and slighting such great salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as hee offereth to restore it,) doe most evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently and most sweetly shine.</p>
               <p>Now, it may be, some will have objections concerning <hi>Pharaoh, Esau,</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>nd the like, that God did raise up <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>he one, that his power, might be
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:170691:65"/> shewed forth upon him, and that he hardned his heart, and hated the other, that the purpose of God ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to election might stand.</p>
               <p>To which, and all such questions is answered two wayes, first, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the divine truth of that Scripture, blessed is the man that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dureth temptation, for when he is tryed he shall receive the Crowne of life, which the Lord hath promised to them that love him; let no man say when he is tempted, I am tempted of God, for God cannot be tempted with evill, neither tempteth he any man, but every man is tempted when he is drawne a way of his owne lusts and inticed, then when lust hath conceived, it bringeth forth sinne, and sinne when it is finished bringeth forth death, <hi>Iames.</hi> 1.12.13, 14, 15.</p>
               <p>Secondly, according to the divine truth of that Scripture, <hi>Behold all
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:170691:66"/> soules are mine, as the soul of the father, so also the soule of the son is mine, the soule that sinneth,</hi> that is, the soule that not only runneth into destru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive sinne, but also rejecteth the remedy, or the soule which is not baptised with a man in Christ, into a living acting God, and a dead pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sive creature, which is the substance and end of this treatise, it shall die E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zek. 18.4. And again, <hi>he that hath the Sonne hath life, and he that hath not the Sonne hath not life. these things have J written unto you, that beleeve on the name of the Sonne of God, that you might know that ye have Eternall life, and that yee may beleev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> on the name of the Sonne of God,</hi> 1 Joh. 5.12, 13. And this is the life and light of a man in Christ, concerning this point, which man in Christ, is like unto the Sonne, who becommeth a will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing patient to his father, according to the divine truth of that scripture,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:170691:66"/> he that beleeveth in me, that is, he that doth not reject his cure, and his cure is to be baptised into a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving active God, and a dead passive creature, though he were dead, yet shall he live. <hi>Iohn,</hi> 11.25. all others are like unto the sonne, which wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, and obstinately rejecteth his cure, according to the divine truth of that scripture, <hi>for God sent not his Sonne into the world, to condemn the world, but that the world through him might be saved, he that beleeveth on him, is not condemned, but he that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeves not is condemned already, because he hath not beleeved, (that it, because he will not come to Christ, that he may have life, and be baptised in a living active God, and a dead passive creature) in the name of the only begotten, sonne of God.</hi> Iohn. 3.17, 18. And againe, <hi>the father loveth the sonne, and hath given all things into his hand, he that beleeveth one the Sonne, hath everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:170691:67"/> life, and he that beleeveth not the Sonne, shall not see life, but the wrath of God abideth one him.</hi> Ioh. 3.35, 36. <hi>therefore, O earth, earth, earth, heare the word of the Lord.</hi> Ieremy. 22.29. <hi>Cast away from you al your transgressi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, whereby you have transgressed, and make you a new heart, and a new spirit, for why will you dye O house of Israel? for I have no pleasure in the death of him that dyeth saith the Lord God, wherefore turne your selves, and live yee, Ezek.</hi> 18.31, 32.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:170691:67"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVI.</hi> That a man in Christ, through Christ, doth feele, know and see in himselfe, in some measure, a spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall Resurrection, which is the true earnest of an exceeding weight of glory unspeakable, and beleeveth the same of all men in Christ. Againe, he doth feele, know, and see in himselfe; that how little a spirituall resurrection is in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self; so little the exceeding weight of glory shall be through all eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, unlesse it be prevented, and beleeveth the same of all men who are in themselves.</head>
               <p>THE rationall creature man, i<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> to be considered in a two fold condition first, in his bodily es<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sentiall
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:170691:68"/> being. Secondly, in his spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall essentiall being.</p>
               <p>In his bodily essentiall being, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve these two things, first, he is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good: because he is made by God, not by himselfe, for whatsoever God maketh or doth, is very Good, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the divine truth of that Scripture, <hi>And God saw every thing that he had made, and behold it was very Good,</hi> Gen. 1.31.</p>
               <p>Therefore man in his bodily es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentiall being, is a comely good and beautifull creature. Secondly, for as much as he is a bodily essentiall being, made by the Eternall Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor and God of nature, it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posible that he shall become an abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ute nothing, or non-being, he may <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ndeed be changed, that is, his body may, yea shall goe to its first matter, of which it was made, but annihila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ed it cannot be, according to the <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ivine truth of that Scripture, <hi>J
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:170691:68"/> know that whatsoever God doth, it shall bee for ever, nothing can be put to it, nor any thing taken from it, and God doth it, that men should feare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him. That which hath beene, it now, and that which is to be, hath already beene, and God requireth that which is past,</hi> Eccl. 3.14, 15.</p>
               <p>Therefore this bodily essentiall good being, although changed and reduced to its originall matter, doth stand in the all-knowledge and sight of its creator through all eternity, either as it hath beene the Temple of his owne Holy Spirit and life, or hath through violence and injury, been made the Temple of the devill, sinne, and death, by the will of man.</p>
               <p>In his spirituall being, observe likewise the same two things, and moreover observe this especially, A man is either A new creature in Christ, or else he is an old man in
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:170691:69"/>
                  <hi>Adam;</hi> according to the divine truth of these Scriptures, <hi>he that is in Christ is a new creature.</hi> 2. Cor. 5 17. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, <hi>for as in Adam all dye, even so in Christ shal al be made alive</hi> 1 <hi>cor.</hi> 15.22.</p>
               <p>If he be in Christ, &amp; Christ in him, then he will dye to his owne will, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, sin, and death, and rise again to the same mind which was also in Christ, that is, to God. holinesse, &amp; everlasting life. If he be in the old<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and <hi>Adam;</hi> then hee will dye to the mind, which was in Christ, that is, to God holinesse and everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting life, and rise againe to his owne will, devill, sin, and death.</p>
               <p>Now as the bodily essence changed, and reduced to its first matter, stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the all-knowledge and fight of its creator through all eternity, either as it hath been the Temple of his owne Holy Spirit and life, or hath through violence and inju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y beene made the Temple of the devill,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:170691:69"/> sin, and death, by the will of man; even so the spiritual essence, after dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solution standeth in the all-know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge &amp; sight of its Creator, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ough all eternity, either as it hath beene the vicegerent and deputy of his holy Spirit, and life in the body, or the Vicegerent and deputy of the divill, finne, and death, by the will of the creature in the body.</p>
               <p>And here is to be observed, in a-divine pondering, that as the two-fold nature of a mā in Christ, namely his bodily and spirituall being, that is, his body and his soule, doth stand in the operative will vertue, all knowledge and sight of their Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor in the time of this momentany <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>fe, the one, as the Temple, the other as the vicegerent, of his owne Holy Spirit and life, they both doe and shal arise unto that exceeding weight of glory, through all eternity, which no mortal creature can expresse. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:170691:70"/> to the divine truth of that Scripture, <hi>Eye hath not seene, nor eare heard, neither have entred into the heart of man, the things which God hath prepared for them that love him, but God hath revealed them unto us, by his Spirit: for the Spirit searcheth all things, yea the deepe things of God.</hi> 1 Cor. 2.9, 10.</p>
               <p>Againe, as the twofold nature of a man in <hi>Adam,</hi> namely, his bodily and spirituall being, that is his body and his soule, doth stand in the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge; and sight of their Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, in the time of this momen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary life, the one as the temple, the other as the vicegerent, of selfe-will devill and sinne, they neither do, nor can arise, unto that exceeding weight of glory, through all eternity, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the divine truth of that Scripture, <hi>but the naturall man, recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth not the things of the Spirit of God, for they are foolishness unto him, neither
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:170691:70"/> can he know them, because they are spiritually discerned,</hi> 1 Cor. 12.14.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVII.</hi> That a man in Christ diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly observeth the Lords day, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though his whole life be and must be led and stated in Sabbath, and beleeveth the same of all men in Christ.</head>
               <p>IT is with a man in Christ and the Lords day in the spirituall talent life, as it is with rich merchants, and such like men in mammon and publique Fairs in the earthly talent life: as into an incorporation, where there is popularity &amp; traffique, there are certaine dayes of the yeare, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted, and called Fayres, in and to which, traffiquers and tradesmen do bring and expose their wares, and outward commodities, to be sold to the advancement of their outward estates, and are very exact and dili<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gent
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:170691:71"/> that neither theeves steale any thing from them; nor cozners give them false money, but observeth su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spected persons by their eyes, and tryeth the gold, and silver of people by their touchstones and weights, and thus are they exercised and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in those fayres or publique market dayes. But now if they got no more traffique and gains through the whole space of the yeare, but what they get in these few dayes of the yeare, they were not able to sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist in their so great earthy under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings, therefore what they doe in the day and time of the Faire, they doe daily, yea, they thinke the day too little and therefore they take part, yea a great part, of the night many times, such insatiable and ardent affection, they have to multiply the earthly talent. So that all their earthy substance, and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, doe not altogether consist or
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:170691:71"/> depend only in and upon these few dayes o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Faires, but also in and upon their daily and nightly traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fique and diligence,</p>
               <p>It is even so with a man in Christ, in his Spirituall talent-life, in the dayes of the weeke and the Lords day, concerning whom in this Point read over againe, and observe the fourth and fift section.</p>
               <p>And moreover, observe here in a divine understanding, that a man in Christ beleeveth that that Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath mentioned, by the man of God, <hi>Moses, saying, remember the Sabbath day to keepe it Holy, &amp;c.</hi> Exod. 20.8. doth tipify and signifie <hi>that r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>st which remaineth to the people <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f God,</hi> Heb. 4 9 which rest is to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aptised into a living acting God, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd a dead passive creature; without whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h he can neither keepe the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, nor be a man in Christ, let him observe one day of seaven never
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:170691:72"/> so strictly, and professe christianity never so eminently, and this may be clearly proved, and confirmed by the true testimony of the out-spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken word of GOD, both before and after <hi>Moses</hi> as in <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel,</hi> the one being a temporary, the other a Sabbaticall worshipper, so in <hi>Iacob</hi> and <hi>Esau,</hi> so in the strict phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>see, and Publican and the like.</p>
               <p>Therefore whosoever would be as <hi>Abel, Iacob,</hi> and the justified Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lican, whosoever would be stated in the true Sabbath, hee must be bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed with a man in Christ, into a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving active God, and a dead passive creature. Otherwise let him do what he will, hee is and willbe as <hi>Cain, Esau,</hi> and the strict Pharisee, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the divine truth of that Scripture, <hi>Hee that is not with mee, is against mee, and hee that gathereth not with me, that is, he that is not bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed in a living active God, &amp; a dead pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sive creature, scattereth</hi> Mat. 12.30.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:170691:72"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVIII.</hi> That a man in Christ doth feel, know, &amp; see in himself, that as he is in Christ, Christ both doth &amp; shall raign upon his earth, that is, the will of the Father in the Son shall in some proportionable measure be done in his earthy body and nature to the subjugating and mortifying thereof, as it shall be done thorow all eternity, in the endlesse spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall life: and beleeveth the same of all men in Christ.</head>
               <p>IEHOVAH, God the Lord, having absolute perfect know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge what man would do, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ever man was created, doth create him, and giveth him a law, that he should feed upon the tree of life, <hi>which was, and is God himselfe:</hi> and abstain from the tree of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:170691:73"/> of good and evill, which <hi>was, and is man himselfe;</hi> But now man <hi>Adam,</hi> runneth after the forbidden Tree, which poysoneth him, and causeth death to have power a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst him, and so he is miserable, poysoned, and mortall, as was also said in the fifteenth Section.</p>
               <p>And Jehovah God, the Lord of mercy, in his eternall love, doth find out a way of mercy, health and life, to compassionate his misery, to expell his poyson, and to change his mortallity into immortallity, and everlasting life; according to the divine truth of that Scripture, <hi>Verily, Verily I say unto you, he that believeth on me, hath everlasting life Ioh.</hi> 6.47. And this lovely way, is the Way, Truth, and Life, even the Lord Christ, the Rock of ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting life; according to this same Scripture, <hi>Whom the Father hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten as himselfe, from all eternity, to
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:170691:73"/> be the salvation and restauration of all that will, and shall by grace, become men in Christ,</hi> and this Christ being the very essence of Heaven, and fulnesse thereof, and the consistence of the earth, <hi>for by him all things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist,</hi> Coloss. 1.17. As the re-stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of all that falleth, and this is only sinfull falling man.</p>
               <p>And as that everlasting light which shineth in, &amp; upon the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of sinfull falling man, hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes shined in and upon the man, as the Sun hath alwayes shined up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Creation; But such hath bin, and such is the darkenesse, that it hath not, nor yet doth, compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the light, which shineth in the darkenesse, and the darknesse comprehendeth it not, <hi>as the man in Christ, John</hi> sayth, Joh. 1.5. And this glorious spirituall heavenly light, is the City set on a Hill, and cannot be hid; it is the bright shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:170691:74"/> Candle, which is not put un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a Bushell, but is set on a Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sticke, to give light to all that are in the house; The Sun and Moone are as sparkling visible figures, of this infinite everlasting light, who giveth their splendor to every crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that is capable to receive it, &amp; offereth it to the poor and base, as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well as to the rich and honourable, aswell to the unjust as to the just, according to the divine truth of that Scripture <hi>For he maketh his Sun to rise on the evill and on the Good, &amp; sendeth rain on the just and unjust, Math.</hi> 3.45. So that the <hi>Day-spring,</hi> and great light Christ, is risen and come into the world, <hi>but men love darknes rather then light,</hi> according to the divine truth of that Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>And this is the condemnation that light is come into the world, and men love darkenes rather then light, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause their deeds were evill,</hi> Joh. 3.19</p>
               <pb n="149" facs="tcp:170691:74"/>
               <p>But now, unto this Lord Chrsst, the true life and light of men, do all the Prophets and apostles, and all other men in Christ, give witnes, and do put to their Seal, that he is a child born to them, a son given un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, and the government is up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his shoulders and he shall call his name <hi>Wonderfull Councellor,</hi> the <hi>mighty God,</hi> the <hi>everlasting Father,</hi> the <hi>Prince of Peace,</hi> the increase of his government &amp; Peace <hi>shall have no end,</hi> Isaiah, 9.6, 7.</p>
               <p>And as the man of God <hi>Esayas,</hi> so also, all the other Prophets, doe in a sweet harmony, breath out, the purity and excellency of this spirituall lovely government, and peaceable Kingdome of this Prince of Peace, in every Soul and body of every man in Christ, in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, and in them all in generall, wheresoever they be dispersed through the habitable world a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:170691:75"/> men, as Wheat amongst the Tares, as Gold in and amongst Fires, as Sheep amongst Wolves.</p>
               <p>And although as they are men, they may within themselves, <hi>Joseph like,</hi> have a seducing Where to tempt, and a <hi>Potiphar</hi> to imprison them; and without themselves <hi>Shimeies</hi> to curse, <hi>Hams</hi> to mocke, and <hi>false Bretheren</hi> to murther, and sell them, in a spirituall malignity, and evill eye, and so being conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the outward man, they hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> trouble both within and withou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> themselves, according to the divine truth of that Scripture, <hi>In the world yee shall have tribulation,</hi> Joh. 16.33. Yet as they are men in Christ, they have <hi>Joseph-like times of refreshment</hi> which fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w from the presence o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Prince of Peace, Christ, who as in his own person, and mysterious exhibiting of himselfe, as the Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conquering King, by goodnes, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience,
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:170691:75"/> and love, did overcome Devil, Sin and Death: Even so he hath done, doth, and shall doe, in all that hath been, are, and shall bee, men in Christ, and members of his mysticall body, to the abollishing of the Kingdome of Devil, Sin and Death, in his members, and to the magnifying and manifestation of his al-glorious Diadem of Grace, and spirituall Kingdome of glory and preheminence.</p>
               <p>But now, as was said before, the carnall worldly mindes of men, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving darknes in stead of true light, and being not able to know the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and excellency of Christ, the Prince of Peace, in his Kingdome, because he is spiritually discerned, as was cited in the Closure of the sixteenth Section, have alwayes in seeing, not seen, and in hearing, not understood, the mystery of the Kingdome of CHRIST, and
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:170691:76"/> therefore it seemes the Pharisees having punctually read over the Prophets, concerning the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Christ, which no carnall mind can know, demanded o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Christ, when the Kingdome of God should come; which they by their carnall accute understanding, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived to come, in an outward hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane splendor and earthly glory; after the manner of man, as man he answered them and said, <hi>The Kingdome of Heaven commeth not with observation,</hi> Luk. 17.20, 21. In the Greek Language it is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is, it commeth not with outward shew, neither shall they say, loe here, or loe there, <hi>For be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the Kingdome of God is within you,</hi> yea the very Disciples them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves in <hi>Acts</hi> 1.6. asked of him saying, <hi>Lord, wilt thou at this time restore again the Kingdome to Jsrael? And he said unto them, it is not for you
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:170691:76"/> to know the times &amp; the seasons, which the Father hath put in his own power, but yee shall receive power after that the Holy Ghost is come upon you, and you shall witnesse unto me, both in Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rusalem, and in all Judea, and in Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria, and to the utmost parts of the earth;</hi> In the Greek language it is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>that is, but you shall receive power of the Holy Ghost, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming upon you,</hi> so that if the Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sees would feele, know, and see, the Kingdome of Christ, they must not thinke to feel, know, and see it in outward shew, after the manner of men, but in an internall spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allity, and if the Lords People will feel, know, and see, the Kingdome restored again to <hi>Jsrael;</hi> that is, the exalting of the Kingdome of <hi>Christ</hi> in the Saints, that is, in men in <hi>Christ</hi> they must feel, know and see it, in the power of the Holy Spirit &amp;
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:170691:77"/> the power of the holy Spirit, &amp; the power of the holy Spirit in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, in an internall spirituallity.</p>
               <p>Some it may be will object, and say. If Christs Kingdome, be but a Spirituall Kingdome, this will be much derogatory to Christ, and contradictory to so many places of Scripture, which holds out such a glorious Raign, as Christ must have upon earth, In a visible Monarchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Kingdome, for a thousand yeares, and the like.</p>
               <p>To which in love I answer; To say so, doth argue much of that which doth rather savour of the things that be of men, then the things that be of God, unlesse the Spirit of God and truth, teach the meaning of Scripture.</p>
               <p>For is it derogatory to the Sun, that it sendeth forth its light, and heat u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>to the earth, and causeth it to be a fruitfull mother of all vege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive,
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:170691:77"/> brute, and rationall creatures, although it selfe be exalted, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant from the earth, in such a vast and mighty distance? Is it not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the glory and excellency of that solary created nature, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce such wonderfull effects, as it doth in such a distance?</p>
               <p>If that glorious created nature were upon the earth, amongst the inferiour creatures, then First, this would be derogatory to its glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and excellent nature, in that its great power and efficacy, should not be manifested, but in-dignifyed and derogated from.</p>
               <p>And secondly, the earth and all the Creatures in it, being Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and earthly, and not able to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure the Immense light, and heate, would all melt and be consumed, which is against the order &amp; State of the visible creation, in which, as in an Image and visible representa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:170691:78"/> of the Creator, the invisible things, of him, from the creation of the World, are clearly seen, being understood by the things that are made, even his eternall power and Godhead.</p>
               <p>Even so is it derogatory to the Creator of the sun, and whole uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versall nature, that he, being the Almighty Spirit, and Being of all Beings, <hi>Who humbleth himselfe, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the things that are in Heaven, and in the earth,</hi> Psal. 113.6. Should manifest his eternall power and Godhead; by filling the Heaven, earth, and Sea, with his goodnesse in such a manner, as becometh the Al-glorious, and infinite power, and Godhead, and as his creatures, each in their own kind may in some small measure be capable of him, and all of them, and especially the rationall creature, to stand in a ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly admiration of his immensity, &amp;
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:170691:78"/> eternity? <hi>For who amongst us shall dwell among everlasting burnings? Esay</hi> 33.14. Or who shall, or can teach the Lord to have a glorious Raign? Shall poor, vain, witlesse creature-man, think that the Lord God Christ shall be an exalted King after the manner of the Kings of clay upon earth? according to the divine truth of that Scripture, <hi>who hath directed the Spirit of the Lord, or being his Councellor, hath taught him? With whom tooke he councell, and who instructed or taught him, in the path of Judgement? And taught him know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and shewed to him the way of understanding?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Behold the Nations are as a drop of a Bucket, and are counted as the small dust of the Ballance; He taketh up the Jsles as a very little thing, and</hi> Leba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non <hi>is not sufficient to burn, nor the</hi> Beasts thereof, <hi>for a Burnt Offering.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>All Nations before him are as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:170691:79"/> and they are counted to him lesse then nothing and vanity; to whom then will you liken God, or what likenesse will you compare him unto? Have yee not known? Have ye not heard? Hath it not been told you from the beginning? Have yee not understood from the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the earth? It is He that sit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth upon the circle of the earth, and the inhabitants thereof are ltke Grasse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoppers; That stretcheth out the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens as a Curtain, and spreadeth them out, as a Tent to dwell in</hi> Esay 40. from 13, to 19. &amp; 21, &amp; 22. <hi>ver.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that the glorious Kingdome of the Lord God Christ is infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly greater, and more glorious, then poor finite creature-man can desire it to be; <hi>For his dominion is an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting dominion, and his Kingdome is from genera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ion to generation,</hi> as the man of God <hi>Daniel,</hi> hath it in his 4<seg rend="sup">th</seg> Chap. <hi>ver.</hi> 34.</p>
               <p>And here is to be observed in a
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:170691:79"/> heavenly uuderstanding, that the Kingdome of the Lord Christ (if it may be lawfull to say so) is two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold; The one is the Kingdome of grace, and this Kingdome is stated in time; The other, is the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of glory, and this Kingdome is stated in eternity.</p>
               <p>Those that are truly stated in the Kingdome of Grace, do through Christ, love Christ their King and Lord, aswell as they love the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of glory: And therefore theirs only is the Kingdome of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; according to the divine truth of that Scripture, <hi>And every one that hath forsaken Houses, or bretheren, or sisters, or father, or mother, or wife, or children, or lands, for my names sake, shall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive an hundred fold, and shall inherit everlasting life,</hi> Math. 19.29. And those that are truly stated in a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving active God, and a dead pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sive creature, do thorow this State,
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:170691:80"/> which State is the Fathers draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) love the will of the Father to be done in them, and not their own, as well as they love Christ, and therefore th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y only are in the Kingdome of Grace; according to the divine truth of that Scripture, <hi>Not every one that saith Lord, Lord, shall enter into the Kingdome of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, but he that doth the will of my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which is in Heaven,</hi> Math. 7.21. And again, <hi>Then said I lo I come, in the Volumne of thy Booke it is written of me, I delight to do thy will, O my God, yea, thy law is within my heart,</hi> Psal. 40.7.8.</p>
               <p>And now, friendly <hi>Reader,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving held out the <hi>Life and Light of a man in Christ,</hi> in judgement and understanding. aswell as in practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call religious performances, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratively with other men, for thy sake and for thy good, without wearying and burthening of thy
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:170691:80"/> memory any further; Here I shall conclude this little Treatise, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting thee and it, to the grouth and grace of God and truth.</p>
               <p>Only let me intreat thus much of thee; Beware how thou readest it; Thou wilt never read it right, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse thou understand it, and thou wilt never understand it, unlesse thou be wise in God, and thou wilt never be wise in God, unlesse thou become a fool in thine own eyes; according to the divine truth of that Scripture, <hi>Let no man deceive himselfe, if any man among you seemeth to be wise in this World, let him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a fool, that he may be wise: for the wisdome of this world is foolishnes with</hi> God, <hi>for it is written, He taketh the wise in their own craftines;</hi> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, <hi>The Lord knoweth the thoughts of the wise that they are vain,</hi> 1. Cor. 3.18, 19.</p>
               <p>Therefore in reading this little
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:170691:81"/> Treatise, as also in all thy other busines, thirst after the Wisdome, and Spirit of God, and thou shalt be satisfyed, according to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine truth of that Scripture, <hi>If any of you lack wisdome, let him aske of</hi> God <hi>that giveth to all men liberally, and upbraideth not, and it shall be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him, but let him aske in faith, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing wavering,</hi> that is, let him be baptised in a living active God, &amp; a dead passive creature, otherwise, he is like a wave of the Sea, dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven with the wind, and tossed, for let not that man thinke, that he shall receive any thing of the Lord; a double minded man is unstable in all his wayes, Jam. 1.5.6, 7, 8. And again, <hi>Jf yee then being evill, know how to give good gifts unto your children, how much more shall your heavenly Father give the Holy spirit, to them that aske him,</hi> that is, who is baptised into a living active God, &amp;
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:170691:81"/> a dead passive Creature.</p>
               <p>And this divine baptism, which is the end &amp; scope of this <hi>little trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise,</hi> and thy chiefest good under the Sun, is here presented unto thee.</p>
               <p>This divine baptisme, what is it else, but the Mariage Dinner of the Kings son? And this little Treatise what is it else, but one of the Kings servants, calling thee who are bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to come?</p>
               <p>If thy Farm, or thy merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize, that is thy selfe, be dearer to thee then this; then Know, that thou art one of those unto whom God and truth saith, <hi>The wedding is ready, but thou who wast bidden, art <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t worthy,</hi> Mat. 22.8. &amp; here I dare confidently perswade thee of two things, the First is, if thou knew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est the gift of God, and what this Kings son is who bids thee come, thou wouldest come, &amp; he would give thee living water, <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.10.</p>
               <pb n="164" facs="tcp:170691:82"/>
               <p>The second is, if thou wilt not come, that is, if thou wilt not have the life &amp; action of the Lord thy God to live &amp; act in thee, which is his glory, &amp; thy eternal happines, But will live and act, in thy own will, life, and action, although thou seeme never so holy and religious, in the eyes of such as thy selfe, and sit down at the Table, that is, be never so observative and frequent in hearing, speaking reading pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and the like, yet thou art that man, which had not on a <hi>Wedding Garment,</hi> and being speechlesse in the sight of God and truth was commanded to be bound hand and foot, and taken away, and cast into utter darknes, where there is weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and gnashing of Teeth, <hi>Math.</hi> 22.13. which I desire the to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered from.</p>
               <p>But if thou with <hi>Ioseph,</hi> who art called to come out of Prison, that is, out of thy selfe, unto good King
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:170691:82"/>
                  <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> that is, unto Christ and his baptisme, shave thy selfe, change thy rayment, and come, then thou art as <hi>Joseph,</hi> that is <hi>increasing,</hi> unto whom <hi>Jsrael</hi> his blessing belongeth saying, <hi>The blessings of thy Father have prevailed above the blessings of my Progenitors, unto the utmost bound of the everlasting Hills, they shall be on the head of</hi> Joseph, <hi>&amp; on the crown of the head of him that was separate from his bretheren;</hi> That is, baptised in a living active God, and a dead passive creature, <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.26.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And the Spirit &amp; the Bride say come, and let him that heareth say come, and let him that is a thirst come, &amp; whosoever will let him take the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of life freely,</hi> Rev. 18.17. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:170691:83"/>
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>I am sorry (Reader) that thou shalt meet with some oversights committed in the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, which lest they should prejudice thy reading, I entreat the to have recourse un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this place, where thou shalt find in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, the particular fault of every page.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the Title Page, for</hi> 1. Cor. 12.13. <hi>read</hi> 1. Cor. 12.31.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the Preface,</hi> for to be a rayler again, <hi>read</hi> against.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In Page</hi> 2. <hi>line</hi> 17. for is life, <hi>read</hi> his life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In Page</hi> 3. <hi>line</hi> 6. for when he said, abide in me, <hi>read</hi> when he said, and sayth abide in me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In Page</hi> 4. <hi>line</hi> 18. for, they that testfy o me, <hi>read</hi> they that testify of me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In Page</hi> 6. <hi>line</hi> 16. <hi>for</hi> bing, <hi>read</hi> being.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In Page</hi> 7. <hi>line</hi> 15. <hi>for</hi> but light, so the Sun, <hi>read,</hi> but light, (for darknes is both contrary to light. and the want of light) so the Sunne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In Page</hi> 10. <hi>line</hi> 11. <hi>for</hi> creatures, but will live, and act in, and thinke, <hi>read</hi> creature, but will live, and act in, and by their own will, and wil-righteousnesse; the false Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, and thinke.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:170691:83"/>
            <p>
               <hi>In Page</hi> 17. <hi>line</hi> 5. <hi>for</hi> the discovery, <hi>read</hi> he true discovery.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the same page, line</hi> 13. <hi>for</hi> thee, <hi>read</hi> the.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In Page,</hi> 21. <hi>line</hi> 7. <hi>for</hi> speak to his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, <hi>read</hi> speak of God to his Neighbour.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In Page</hi> 22. <hi>line</hi> 15. <hi>or elsewhere for</hi> redi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, <hi>read</hi> ridiculous.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In Page</hi> 52. <hi>line</hi> 9. <hi>for</hi> the Divine, <hi>read</hi> this Divine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In Page</hi> 53, <hi>line</hi> 10. <hi>for</hi> understanding, <hi>read</hi> understandings.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In Page</hi> 67. line 2. <hi>for</hi> moton, <hi>read</hi> motion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In Page</hi> 74. <hi>line</hi> 17. <hi>for</hi> generation and, <hi>read</hi> generation in, and.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In Page</hi> 75. <hi>line</hi> 18. <hi>for</hi> bapti, <hi>read</hi> baptised.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In Page</hi> 77. <hi>line</hi> 6. <hi>for</hi> yet, <hi>read</hi> get.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In Page</hi> 78. <hi>line</hi> 24. <hi>for</hi> great, <hi>read</hi> greater.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In Page</hi> 83. <hi>line</hi> 10. <hi>for</hi> same, <hi>read</hi> Sun. In the same <hi>Page, line</hi> 18. <hi>for</hi> Ante-father, <hi>read</hi> Antifather.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In Page</hi> 87. <hi>line</hi> 3. <hi>for</hi> an, <hi>read</hi> and.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In Page</hi> 91. <hi>line</hi> 14. <hi>for</hi> externall, <hi>read</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In Page</hi> 92. <hi>line</hi> 17. <hi>for</hi> spirituall, <hi>read</hi> spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In Page</hi> 97. <hi>line</hi> 20 <hi>for</hi> petaining <hi>read</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In Page</hi> 100. <hi>line</hi> 13. <hi>for</hi> as a loving, <hi>read</hi> to a loving. <hi>In the same page, line</hi> 20. <hi>for</hi> God, <hi>read</hi> good.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>